No.
沒有.
donated to the Commission's made in China a
donated to the Commission's made in China a
research provided by the government city
research provided by the government city
and some political participants from China
and some political participants from China
have passed this task.
have passed this task.
why not is a
why not is a
whole woman
whole woman
moisturizer
moisturizer
effective
effective
only
only
Welcome everyone to join the feast of knowledge tonight
歡迎大家來參加今天晚上的知識饗宴
The topic of today's feast of knowledge is
今天知識饗宴的那個題目是
Holy Heaven hand dance community
聖屬天手跳社區
Then let’s talk about the heat hazards and PM2.5 that are right in front of us
然後要談談近在眼前的熱危害及PM2.5
so we know that
所以我們知道說
We live in Taipei City, New Taipei City
我們生活在新北市台北市
This densely populated urban area
這個人口比較密集的都會區域
For our health in this environment
對於我們的健康這個環境上
There are many manufacturers
廠商有很多
Manufacturers are very dangerous
廠商是非常危險的事情
especially in this summer
尤其在這種夏天
hot weather
天氣又熱
So what we often see
所以我們常看到的
health hazard
健康會有所危害的
are these hot temperatures
是這些熱溫度
High temperature and so-called PM2.5
高溫還有所謂的PM2.5
So the Academia Sinica in this respect
所以中央研究院在這方面
There are also some basic research
也有一些基礎性的研究
Some researchers are focusing on these
有些研究人員在專注在這些
Greater health
更大重健康
related topics
有關的課題
with some more basic
用一些比較基本的
basic scientific research
基礎的科學研究
hope to clarify
希望能夠釐清
There are some special situations
這裡面一些特殊的狀況
also can hope to be able to say
也是能夠希望能夠說
tell everyone
告訴大家
How do we avoid these hazards
我們怎麼樣去避免這些危害
so today's speaker
所以今天的演講者
It's researcher Long Shijun
是龍士俊研究員
He is our Academia Sinica
他是我們中研院
environmental change
環境變遷
research center
研究中心的
a teacher researcher
一位老師 研究員
He is from National Taiwan University
他是在從台大
The first graduate of science from a large enterprise
大企科學第一名畢業的
sit down please give me three minutes
請坐 我們先給我三分鐘
at Harvard University
在美國哈佛大學
School of Public Health
公共衛生學院
Got a Ph.D.
拿到了博士
in a famous
是在一個很有名的
a chair professor
一位講座教授
Under John Spankles' door
John Spankles的門下
he has been for a long time
他在長期以來
Finally, 15 years of expertise is in the study of these thermal hazards
到終於15年都在專長就是在研究這些熱危害
air pollution
空氣污染
These assessments of these hazards of these risks in this environment
這個環境的這些風險的這些危險的這些評估
that uses the scientific method
那用的是科學的方法
Because some organic chemistry analysis is to be done
因為要做一些有機化學的分析
To design the instruments for these detections
要去設計這些探測的儀器
especially in many specialties
尤其在很多專長
His expertise is mainly in the analysis of the components of organic coke
他的專長主要在那有機氣焦的成分的分析
Because of his achievements on such an important subject
在因為他這些對這種重要課題上面的成果
In 2004, he won the Qiusheng Award of the Taiwan Air-Coke Society
在2004年曾經得過台灣氣焦學會的秋生獎
He's doing a lot of things on this side of public service at the same time
他在同時在這個為公共服務這邊也做了很多事情
Participate in committees related to environmental quality or government agencies in Taipei City
在台北市環境品質或是政府機構有關的委員會裡頭都有參與
so today
所以今天
he came back and told us
他回來告訴我們
probably explain
大概要去解釋一下
I now tell everyone
我現在對大家人大家都聽到
Very familiar with what is PM2.5
很熟悉什麼是PM2.5
contained in
裡頭包含的
what is basic science
基礎科學是什麼東西
Then our current
然後我們現在的
heat hazard is what we are now
熱威害就是我們現在
today
今天
at this
在這個
July
七月
The temperature we must face
我們一定會面臨的溫度
and the quality of our air
還有我們的空氣的品質
so i thought i would
所以我想我就
don't spend too much time
都不花太多的時間
us
我們
had a great speech
有一場很精彩的演講
so we ask everyone
所以我們請大家
Welcome with loud applause
樂烈掌聲歡迎
Researcher Long Shijun
龍師俊研究員
Give us today's Sisi Banquet
給我們今天的思思小宴
thank you all
謝謝大家
Thank you Vice President for your introduction
謝謝副院長的介紹
Thank you all for your support on such a hot day
也謝謝大家在這麼大熱天的
Come to this evening
這個傍晚來參加這一場
this little feast of knowledge
這個知識的小宴
When I was in National Taiwan University
我在台大大氣的時候
actually learned by
學的其實是以
this
這個
air mass
氣團
How to transmit How to cause the diffusion of pollutants
怎麼樣傳輸 怎麼樣去造成污染物的擴散
this aspect
這方面
but i'm in the harvard school of public health
但是我在哈佛公共衛生學院裡面
What we want is actually from a human perspective
我們想求的其實是從以人為角度
for departure
為出發
It's human-centered, let's talk about it
就是人為中心 然後來看說
What kind of environmental factors
到底有什麼樣的環境因子
will affect my health
會影響到我的健康
OK so this neighborhood we live in
OK 所以我們所居住的這個社區
In fact, it is the environment that most affects our quality of life.
其實是最會影響到我們生活品質的環境
So that's what we're most concerned about
所以也就是我們最關心的個客題
The type of living in this community in Asia
亞洲的這個社區居住的型態
Not the same as Europe and the United States
跟歐美不太一樣
everyone knows
大家都曉得
because we are densely populated
因為我們是人口密集
then densely populated places
然後人口稠密的地方
Traffic is heavy again
交通又反繁忙
So our doorstep
所以我們其實家門口
often within an hour
常常一個小時之內
Thousands of vehicles will pass by
大概幾千輛車子會經過
Unlike the existing residential areas in Europe and the United States
不像歐美的存住宅區
they may be within a day
他們可能一天之內
ten cars that will pass
會經過的十輛車
His own and his neighbor's
就他自己的跟他鄰居的
the exposure
這個曝露的情況
It's just that the exposure is completely different.
就是曝顯的情況完全不一樣
So we live in communities where there are many
所以我們生活的社區中有很多
like this close at hand
像這種近在眼前的
The source of traffic pollution is the catering industry that we pass through every day to and from get off work
交通污染源 將我們每天上下班會經過的餐飲業
Even public temples or some small factories
甚至是公廟或者是一些小工廠
These are all sources of pollution that are in sight
這些都是進在眼前的污染源
When I came back to my country, I found that these Asians are very special
我回國之後發現這些亞洲非常特別
And it is very important source of pollution to our life
而且對我們生活非常重要的污染源
but few studies
卻很少有人研究
so i just jumped in
所以我就一頭跳進來
Hope to use a scientific and systematic way
希望用一個科學性系統性的方式
to study these pollution sources
來研究這些污染源
What is the incremental exposure to us?
到底對我們的曝顯增量有多少
What is the impact factor behind it
它背後有什麼影響因子
How can we reduce its impact
我們怎麼樣能降低它的影響
Protect our own health
後來保障我們自己的健康
At the same time, I myself was born with an atmosphere
同時我自己也是大氣器出生
So under climate change
所以在氣候變遷之下
everyone's getting hotter
大家的越來越熱
So for thermal hazards I can also combine
所以對熱危害剛好我也可以結合
Expertise in Atmospheric Sciences and Public Health
大氣科學跟公共衛生的專長
to discuss
來加以探討
So today's talk will take these two as the topic
所以今天的話就以這兩個為題目
is how we go deep
就是我們怎麼深入的
How does my team go deep into the community
我的團隊怎麼深入社區
Then study the thermal hazards in front of you and follow the 2.5
然後研究進在眼前的熱危害跟偏2.5
I'll start with this
那我就先從這個
Start with thermal hazards
先從熱危害開始接受
at least
至少起
Well, this is, this is no longer news to everyone.
那這個是 這個已經大家不是新聞了
That is, every year, we break records in high temperature.
就是每一年的話 我們都高溫破紀錄
OK, it's been three years in a row, this opinion says yes
OK 已經連續三年 這個認為說是
hottest ever hottest ever and then set new highs three years in a row
史上最熱 史上最熱 然後連續三年寫下新高
OK so climate change becomes the norm
OK 所以氣候變遷變成一個常態
So we will face more and more frequent
所以我們就會面臨越來越頻繁的
This heat wave continues at this high temperature
這個熱浪持續的這個高溫
Then Taiwan will be connected with the subtropical zone
那台灣會與亞熱帶
Therefore, in the words of ordinary people, it is likely to think that
所以一般人的話 很可能認為說
I grew up in such a hot environment
我從小長大 就是在這麼熱的環境底下
I have long adapted to the heat
我早就適應了熱
So it shouldn't have any effect on my health
所以對我健康應該不會有什麼影響
OK, when I talked to you about heat hazards more than ten years ago
OK 十幾年前我跟大家談熱危害的時候
The general reaction is like this, including doctors OK
一般的反應都是這樣 包括醫生 OK
let's see
那我們看一下
This was ten years ago OK
這個是十年前 OK
there is sad news out
有不幸的消息傳出來
Three days of heat killed three old farmers OK
連三天有熱死三個老農夫 OK
After this incident, everyone realized that
從這次事件之後大家才意識到說
Taiwan may also experience heat hazards
台灣也可能會有熱危害的情況
Then every year this
那後來每一年的這個
Such unfortunate things happen almost every summer vacation
暑假幾乎都有這樣子不幸的事情發生
Then this is this year
那這個是今年的
ok the latest
ok 最近的
Elderly man hangs clothes for three hours and passes out due to heatstroke
老人家曬衣服三小時中暑昏迷
And he was also in the
而且他還因為導臥在
this asphalt road
這個柏油路上
Wounded hands twice
雙手還二度著傷
When I was sent to the hospital, my temperature soared above 40 degrees.
送醫的時候體溫飆破四十度
Well, such an unfortunate case
好 這麼不幸的這個案例
Fortunately, he was rescued later.
那還好後來人事救回來了
Then you might think that this is an isolated case
那您可能會認為說這個是個案
Ok, what about the statistics from the Ministry of Welfare?
ok 那這個慰福部的統計呢
In fact, it's only halfway through July
其實七月才過一半
Nearly 300 people in Taiwan
全台近三百人
All sent to the ER for heat hazard, thermal injury.
都因為熱危害 熱傷害而送急診
ok more than ten years ago
ok 十多年前
When we first started to study the issue of thermal hazards
我們剛開始要研究熱危害的議題的時候
The Ministry of Health and Welfare does not have one like this
衛福部根本還沒有這樣子的一個
Notification System of Thermal Hazards
熱危害的通報系統
now have
現在有了
because it is true
是因為確實這個
Even the doctors in the emergency room will encounter many
連急診室的醫生都會有碰到很多的
An example of an emergency room visit due to a thermal hazard
是因為熱危害送急診的例子
ok that's in the whole
ok 那在整個
What about the World Health Organization?
這個世界衛生組織呢
Based on our current scientific evidence
根據我們目前的科學證據
to estimate future climate change scenarios
來推估在未來的氣候變遷的情境
Let me explain this A1B to you
這個A1B跟大家解釋一下
In fact, it is still a medium carbon emission
其實還是一個中等排碳
Even if it's not the most carbon-intensive situation
就算不是一個排碳最厲害的情況
Even under a moderate carbon emission scenario
即使在一個中度排碳的情況之下
in Asia
在亞洲地區
Regardless of whether it is a high-income country in the Asia-Pacific
不管是亞太高收入國家
or East Asia or Southeast Asia
或是東亞或東南亞
Cases of additional deaths due to the impact of climate change
因為氣候變遷的衝擊所額外致死的案例
The number of thermal hazards is the largest
都是以熱危害數為最多
much higher than other
遠遠高於其他因為
Infectious diseases caused by climate change
氣候變遷所造成的傳染病
Style hot, hot, warm, thick and aggressive, etc.
風格熱、熱、暖、濃及激勢等等
That's because the current high temperature is long
那是因為現在的高溫長長的話
Soar to 38, 40 in one go
一下就飆到38、40
It is far more than our body can bear
它遠遠超過我們人體所能夠負荷
Even these Asia-Pacific high-income countries
即使這些亞太高收入國家
We say that Taiwan belongs to this
我們講台灣是屬於這個
Although we have a good infrastructure
雖然我們有很好的基礎設施
We have good medical resources
我們有很好的醫療的資源
But when the ambient temperature is so high
但是當環境溫度這麼高的時候
unless we don't go out
除非我們都不出門
Unless we're all locked in an air-conditioned room
除非我們都鎖在冷氣房
Otherwise we'd all likely be exposed to heat hazards
否則的話我們很可能都會遭受到熱危害
that would make sense
那就會有意義
some weaker ones
一些身體比較弱的
Including children, the elderly, pregnant women
包括是小孩子 老人 孕婦
He already had this cardiovascular disease
他本來就有這個心臟血管疾病的人
He will be exposed to heat hazards
他就會遭受到熱危害
it may cause misfortune
可能會因此而造成不幸
So whether this is estimated in 2030
那這個不管是2030年的推估
Same as the 2050 projection
跟2050年的推估都是
Thousands of people will be exposed to heat hazards
有幾千人會因此而遭到熱危害
so the countries of the world
所以世界各國
Therefore put this for thermal hazards
因此把這個對於熱危害的
Countermeasures
因應對策
is how we adjust
就是我們怎麼調適
OK response
OK 因應
Future climate variability like this
這樣子的未來氣候變異
challenge to us
對我們的挑戰
as one of their top priorities
是當作他們的首要的一個任務
OK
OK
According to this methodology, Taiwan
那台灣根據這樣的方法論的話
We also made our own estimates
我們自己也做了推估
There are probably hundreds of them every year.
每一年的話大概也會有幾百個
Cases of additional deaths due to thermal hazards
是因為熱危害額外致死的案例
Most of them are also concentrated in people over the age of 65.
那多半都是也是集中在65歲以上
then you might think
那您可能覺得說
is this overrated
這是不是高估
People around me don't seem to have
我身邊的人好像不會有
How to feel the heat hazard
怎麼樣感受到熱危害
We go to work early every day at most
我們每天頂多就是早點上班
You'll be fine if you hide in an air-conditioned room
躲進冷氣房就沒事了
OK to share with you
OK 跟大家分享一下
what we do in this community
我們在這個社區做的
Actually go into people's homes to do measurements
實際上進到人家家戶裡面去做測量
This is the past few years we have been in the two areas of Gaoping, Greater Taipei
這是過去幾年我們在大台北高平兩個地區
We recruited 62 volunteers in three communities
三個社區我們招募62個這個志願者
Let's go to his house to measure
我們去做他家裡去測量
The temperature between the outdoors of his house and his indoor living room
他家戶室外跟他室內客廳的這個溫度
OK, then we have the same 62 data
OK 那我們這是同樣62個數據
We use different groupings
我們是用不同的分組
like boys and girls
像男生女生啊
This age, North and South, etc.
這個年齡啊 南北啦等等
Then I want to point out that it is the last item.
那我這邊要特別指出是最後一項
He opened the window and turned on the air conditioner.
他這個開窗跟開冷氣這個部分
Of course we all know
當然我們大家都曉得
Turning on the air conditioner is of course lower than the temperature with the windows open
開冷氣當然是比開窗的這個溫度要低
But have you seen their temperature?
可是大家有沒有看到一下他們的這個溫度
OK, this one with the window open
OK 這個開窗的這個
There are three households, and it's almost 40 degrees.
家戶有三個都將近要40度了
OK this isn't our first time at home
OK 這個不是我們第一次在家裡
40 degrees is measured inside the house
人家家戶裡面測到40度
Actually many times
其實好多次
When I came back from the first test, I told my assistant about yours
第一次測回來的時候我就跟我助理講說你那個
There's something wrong with that thermometer of yours, take it in and have it calibrated again.
你那個溫度計有問題拿去再去校正一下
He said the calibration is fine
他說校正的沒問題
It's not about his abandonment
不是他遺棄的問題
That house is really 40 degrees
是那個家戶真的是到40度
I said why the air conditioner is not turned on at 40 degrees?
我說為什麼40度還不開冷氣啊
how can you bear it
怎麼受得了啊
He said that grandpa told me
他說那個阿公跟我講說
He only turns on the air conditioner when his grandson comes
他只有孫子來的時候才開冷氣
usually he is at home
平常他在家裡
He thinks it's amazing that I've lived like this all my life
他覺得我一輩子都是這樣子過有什麼了不起
I'm used to it
我都已經適應了
this is a reason
這是一個原因
One reason is that the air conditioner is too costly
在一個原因的話是覺得冷氣太耗錢了
too expensive
太花錢了
So he can't bear to leave
所以他也捨不得開
and some housewives
還有一些家庭主婦
He's actually at home because he needs to spend his own money
他在家裡其實因為要花自己的錢
So they don't turn on the air conditioner
所以他們是不開冷氣的
Compared with our usual white-collar stage
跟我們平常這個白領階期
Blow on the air conditioner when we go to work
我們去上班的時候吹冷氣
the situation is very different
情況是很不一樣
So Taiwan does have such a situation
所以台灣確實有這樣的情況
We are among the 62 defenders
我們在62位受防者當中
There are only 13 people who turn on the air conditioner
只有13位他是開冷氣的
And he is actually in the middle of the air-conditioning
而且他其實這個開冷氣的當中
Because we measured and found
因為我們測量之後發現
His indoor and outdoor temperature
他這個室內跟室外的溫度
In fact, the correlation is as high as 0.9
其實相關性很高達到0.9
We just wondered how is it possible?
我們就想說怎麼有可能啊
If you turn on the air conditioner for a long time
你如果冷氣開了好一陣子
Shouldn't the temperature be this low?
不是應該溫度這樣低了嗎
First, they didn't turn on the air conditioner very low.
第一個 他們冷氣沒有開很低
This is the first point because it saves power
這是第一點 是因為比較省電
The second one is very honest if there are several
第二個 有好幾位就很誠實的
talk to my assistant
跟我的助理講說
that's because you're coming
那是因為你要來了
So we were the first ten minutes
所以我們就是前十分鐘
just turn on the air conditioner
才把冷氣打開
for going to meet him
因為去迎接他
just feel sorry
就是覺得不好意思
Someone has guests and the house is very hot
人家客人來了 然後家裡很熱
OK so in this case
OK 所以是在這個情況之下
So their correlation calculation is quite high
所以他們的相關計算相當高
So this means that
所以這是代表就是說
We are actually in this ordinary household
我們其實在這個一般家戶中
There are many situations that do exist
有很多確實存在的情況
is that they may all be potential
就是他們可能都是潛在的
Possible Groups of Thermal Hazards
熱危害的可能族群
Because they generally don't turn on the air conditioner at home
因為他們在家裡一般都不開冷氣
ok so this is the show saying
好 所以這是顯示說
our taiwan words
我們台灣的話
In fact, we have to formulate this dark countermeasure
其實要擬定這個陰陰對策
is to adjust
就是調適
The government needs to adjust the strategy
政府要做調適策略
is very very important
是相當相當重要的
then our scientific community
那我們科學界
How can we help the government to
怎麼樣能夠幫助政府去
What about the adjustment strategy for this thermal hazard?
嚴謹這個熱危害的調適策略呢
The first thing we can do is
我們可以做的第一個是
we can do this
我們可以做這個
In this rigorous climate change adaptation strategy
在這個嚴謹氣候變遷的調適策略
Advance Scientific Assessment Process
先期的科學評估的過程
Vulnerability Assessment
就是叫做脆弱度評估
The vulnerability assessment
這個脆弱度評估
it's easy to say
講起來很簡單
But it's also very complicated and difficult to do
可是也很複雜也很難做
The first is to figure out what are the highly vulnerable communities
第一個就是要搞清楚哪些是高脆弱的社群
Vulnerability by definition
脆弱度就定義來講
Briefly introduce to you
簡單跟大家介紹
It actually has three aspects
它其實分三個面向
This is also very intuitive
這個也很直覺
The first is how much heat hazard I'm exposed to
第一個就是我受到多少熱危害的程度
This is exposure
這個是曝顯量
but the same exposure
可是同樣的曝顯量
some people can stand it some people can't
有些人受得了有些人不行
For example, if I have a heart vessel
譬如說我如果有心臟血管原來的
I'm weak if I have a disease
就有疾病的話我就是很弱
So the same heat is for me
所以同樣的熱對我來講
may not be able to bear
可能就受不了
OK
OK
So this sensitive word
所以這個敏感性的話
It's a person's physique
就是個人的體質
personal physical characteristics
個人的身體特徵
including the older
包括說年長的
pregnant women
懷孕的婦女
fetus
胎兒
very young child
很幼小的小孩
this is sensitivity
這就是敏感性
Or the underprivileged who are involved in sperm, etc.
或者是涉精的弱勢者等等
if you come again
再來的話是
Responsiveness should also be considered
還要考量是因應能力
words of resilience
因應能力的話
means
就是表示
Is there any way for me to deal with the heat hazard from the outside world?
我這個有沒有辦法去因應說外界這個熱危害
I hid in the air-conditioned room
我躲進冷氣房
This is the best countermeasure
這個是最好的因應對策
OK so I can do it in my profession
OK 那所以我以我的職業的話我有辦法這樣做到
But many people's occupations cannot do this.
可是很多人的職業沒有辦法這樣做到
So it may not be able to cope well
所以它因應能力可能就不好
So which are
那所以 哪些是
That's because the sensitivity is mostly a matter of personal constitution
那因為敏感性多半是個人的體質的問題
So the main thing we want to discuss here is
所以我們這邊最主要要探討的就是
Who are the high-risk groups
哪些人是高負險的社群
Who are the low ability groups
哪些人是低因能力的社群
Can we find out the features
我們是不是可以把特徵找出來
Therefore, social welfare units can target these
所以社福單位的話可以針對這些
The words of this highly sensitive and vulnerable community
這個高敏感高脆弱的社群的話
Then come here and do something better
然後來這個做一些比較好的
This measure of prevention, sanitation, etc.
預防 衛教等等的這個措施
The questions we have to answer then include
那我們還要回答的問題包括
Are the people actually
那實際上民眾是不是
He actually suffers from heat hazard levels
他實際上遭受到熱危害程度
is it really serious
是不是真的很嚴重
Are there any high-risk communities?
那有沒有高負險的社群存在
what is his actual risk
他實際的負險怎麼樣
that for
那為了
If we're going to talk about thermal hazards
這個我們要探討熱危害的話
but more important
但更重要
how to deal with it
要是怎麼樣去因應它
OK
OK
Coping
那只有因應對策
In terms of countries around the world
就世界各國來講
Most Important Coping Strategies
最重要的因應對策
All thermal hazard warnings
都是熱危害預警
OK
OK
just to tell you in advance
就是在事先告訴你說
heat is coming
熱量要來了
We have heat for days
我們連續好幾天熱量
So everyone spend less time outside
所以大家減少在外面待的時間
or drink more water
或者是多喝水
then wipe your face more
然後多擦臉
sweating etc.
出汗等等
is to use this prior prevention
就是用這個事先的預防
So if we want to have this
那如果說我們要有這個
word on heat warning system
熱預警系統的話
Which one is the appropriate heat hazard index for Taiwan?
哪一個是合適台灣的熱危害指標
So if we're going to issue a heat warning like this
那如果我們要發佈這樣的熱預警
We need to find the appropriate pre-limit value
我們就要找出合適的預限值
So this is all science
所以這個都是科學界
can help to answer this question
可以幫助來回答的這個問題
this is our team
這是我們這個團隊
this direction of this effort
這個努力的這個方向
so let me introduce
那所以我先介紹一下
is how we go
就是我們怎麼樣去
Find out which are the most vulnerable communities
找出來哪一些是高脆弱的社群
OK
OK
In fact, in the past few years, if we
我們其實在過去幾年的話
very hard
都很辛苦的
we follow this survey
我們跟這個調查
Cooperation with the Research Center of the Academy of Industry
眾業院的調研中心合作
Telephone interview conducted by OK Face-to-face interview
OK 進行的電訪 面訪
then we also
那我們也
Trying to take advantage of this relatively advanced network
試圖利用這個比較先進的這個網路
The Crowdsourcing Approach The Information Science Approach
群眾外包的方法 資訊科學的方法
Cooperate with the teachers of the information center
跟資訊所的老師合作
Ways to do research with mobile phones Online research
用手機調查 網路調查的方式
In fact, if it is a telephone interview or a face-to-face interview
那其實如果說是電訪 面訪的話
Of course the cost is high
花的成本當然是很高
OK, online surveys are cheaper than mobile surveys
OK 那網路調查跟手機調查比較便宜
And it can have 4,000 or 8,000 copies in two weeks
而且呢 它兩個禮拜之內居然可以有4000或8000份
wow so fast so great
哇 好快喔 好棒喔
So I can after the heat hazard comes
所以我可以在熱危害來的之後
go to this survey
去這個調查
this is very good
這是非常好的
what a pity
可惜的是什麼呢
everyone will know
大家就知道了
Who will actually fill in these questionnaires on the Internet and on the mobile phone?
會真正是在網路上跟手機上填這些問卷資料的是誰
just young people
就是年輕人嘛
Young people are not a highly vulnerable group of heat hazards at all.
年輕人根本不是熱危害的高脆弱社群啊
so it becomes
所以就變成是說
This method is scientifically feasible
這個方法科學上可行
We also built something like this
我們也建立了這樣子的
Crowdsource this survey method
群眾外包這個調查的方法
Unfortunately not so suitable for use in this heat hazard
可惜不是那麼適合在這個熱危害來使用
So we later or later
所以我們後來還是以來
The information for this interview was done at a lot of cost.
這個花很多的成本做的這個面訪的資料
In terms of noodle shops
以面坊來講
eighty percent
百分之八十的
we smoked this
我們抽的這個
Respondent's words
受訪者的話
would reject us
會拒絕我們
So we're going to draw 10,000
所以我們要抽一萬個
The middle two thousand finally succeeded
中間兩千個終於成功了
Telephone visits have a higher rate of giant visits
電訪的巨訪率更高
90%
是九成
But these actual visits
可是這些實際的訪問
is able to give us
是能夠給我們
very in-depth information
非常深入的資料
Let's go into more detail
讓我們去做比較細緻的
scientific discussion
科學上的探討
The words here are also sincere, please everyone
這邊的話也是誠懇的拜託大家
If you get a call some day
如果您哪一天接到電話的
investigate or
調查或者是
remember to the end
有記性到底
Plus say you want to interview
加說要面訪的話
please say yes
麻煩你說同意
science that can help us
可以幫助我們的科學
Research
研究
So we base this
所以我們根據這個
The interview information
面訪的這個資料
explore
探討
High-risk groups and low-hard ability groups
高迫險社群跟低硬能力社群的
feature
特徵
When these features are many
當這些特徵有很多
Sincerely
誠懇情況的話
Our first focus is
我們先著重的是
He was forced to spend a lot of time outside
他被迫要在室外待的時間比較長
What are the characteristics of which communities?
那是哪些社群的 哪些特徵呢
OK, the male is less educated
OK 那男性教育程度低
Part-time jobs for remote witnesses
偏遠相證的民眾 兼職工作
Also engaged in these industries
還有是從事這些行業的
Agriculture, forestry, cloud, wood, mining, manufacturing and construction
農林雲木礦業製造 營造
or wholesale shipping
或者是批發運輸
Some of them are known from the literature
那有一些都是文獻上知道的
but some are not
可是有一些並不是
Include wholesale shipping like this
包括像這個批發運輸
We thought he drove a big truck
我們以為他開個大卡車
He actually has air conditioning in the car
他其實在車子裡面有冷氣
We actually asked a few drivers
我們還實際上去問過幾個司機
He said some cars were simply too old
他說有的車子根本太老舊
I can't turn on the air conditioner at all
我根本沒辦法開冷氣
I turn on the air conditioner and the engine gets wet
我開冷氣那個引擎就很濕溺
this is a little
這是一點
The second point he said
第二點的話他說
In fact, many of us smoke
其實我們很多人都抽煙
so if we smoke
所以我們抽煙的話
The windows won't close at all
根本窗戶不會關的
So they won't turn on the air conditioner
所以他們也就不會開冷氣
Because you didn't turn on the air conditioner
因為你開冷氣的也沒有
OK so they become
OK 所以他們就變成是
longer time outdoors
在戶外的時候比較長
They spend more time in the sun
他們受日曬的時間比較長
It's like this, this has such characteristics
是這樣子的這個有這樣的特徵
Then everyone because of the cold
那就各位因為冷氣
In this regard, I just mentioned
在這方面的話 剛也剛提到了
In fact, some households do not have air-conditioning or use less air-conditioning
其實真的是有家戶是沒有冷氣或是少開冷氣的
Like the family elders who don't have a high description in this family, etc.
像這個家庭說明不高的族居長者等等
As for these materials, we will also provide them to the Ministry of Health and Welfare’s Social Housing and Family Affairs Bureau.
那這些資料的話 我們也提供給這個衛福部的社會居家庭署
their social workers said
他們的社工人員 他們說
Their social workers have already made calls in hot weather.
他們社工人員其實已經在熱天的時候都有打電話
To care for these elders in the ethnic group to remind them that
去關懷這些族居老人來提醒他們說
Drink plenty of water, rest more, don't go out in hot weather, etc.
要多喝水 多休息 熱天不要出去等等的
OK, everyone can do this
OK 都有做到這樣子的
Okay, let's take a look at our province's actual
好 那我們看一下 我們全省其實
More than 2000 respondents
2000多個受訪者
To find these more than 2,000 respondents, we must not be alone.
這個要找到這2000多個受訪者 我們一定不可能是我一個人去找
So we are also with this research center
所以我們就是 也是跟這個調研中心
Together, 25 interviewers were trained and then
共同是訓練了25位訪員 然後
Visit these 50 villages across the province
拜訪全省這50個村裡
Then our execution period is from the genus to the autumnal equinox
那我們的執行期間的話 是從小屬到秋分
In fact, there may be autumn tigers in the middle
其實這個中間都還有可能是有秋老虎的時候
Then this visit
那這個這次的訪問
It's actually very special
其實也是很特別
This is the first time environmental science and social scientists have collaborated
這是第一次環境科學跟社會科學家合作
So these interviewers' questionnaires were
所以這些訪問員的問卷裝
Not just to ask social questions
不只是要問社會的問題
Also ask environmental science questions
還要問環境科學的問題
Even more powerful
更厲害的是
they actually
他們其實還
we also train them
我們還訓練他們
Help us carry the temperature and humidity in quarantine
幫我們攜帶檢疫式的溫溼度
and photodetector
以及光復檢測器
to monitor the environmental conditions inside and outside their homes
來檢測他們家戶內外的環境條件
OK
OK
So you see these little boxes in front of you
所以大家看到前面這些小盒子
It's all these quarantine-style environments.
都是這些檢疫式的環境的
Talk about quarantine
講是講檢疫式
But it is the precision that must be able to conform to scientific data
但是它是精密度是要能夠符合科學數據的
OK
OK
The data can also be transmitted
那資料也是能夠傳輸下來
good
好
That's how it works
那其實這樣子的做法
We also provide
我們也提供給
The person from the family of the Ministry of Health and Welfare
那個衛福部社家屬的人
we just say
我們就說
your social worker
你們的社工員
during home visits
家訪的時候
Maybe take a quarantine test with you.
可能也可以帶個檢疫式的去測一下
The indoor and outdoor temperature of his old man's house
他這個老人家的家裡的室內外溫度
This will help them clarify
這樣可以幫他們的釐清
What kind of old people
到底哪些老人家
In fact, I usually don't turn on the air conditioner at home.
其實平常在家裡是不怎麼開這個冷氣的
OK
OK
So you can find this advanced
所以大家可以找出這個高級的
vulnerable communities
脆弱的社群
What we are talking about today is testing
我們今天提到的是檢測
Detect environmental conditions inside and outside the home
檢測家戶室內外的環境條件
means we are testing
表示我們在檢測
the extent of its thermal hazard
它的熱危害的程度
We want him to understand the extent of its heat hazard
我們希望他了解它熱危害的程度
So we're going to the next question
所以我們就要接到下一個問題
What is the appropriate indicator of thermal hazards in Taiwan
就是什麼是合適台灣地區的熱危害的指標
This is a few years ago in New York
這個是紐約十八前幾年的
Rarely does the mass media address this
難得大眾媒體會針對這個
Proposed that heat is not just high temperature
提出說熱不只是溫度高而已
The terrifying combination of temperature and humidity is even more terrifying
溫度跟濕度的恐怖組合才更可怕
So we all know in Taiwan
所以我們在台灣都曉得
If also under the condition of high temperature
如果同樣在高溫的情況之下
if the humidity is high
如果濕度很高的時候
We can't sweat out
我們排的汗排不出去
So we will feel more heat and pressure
所以我們會感受到更熱壓力更大
OK more sad
OK 更難過
So humidity is a very important factor to consider
所以濕度學的是一個很重要的考慮因子
in meteorology
在氣象學上
We learned it when we were sophomores
我們大二的時候就學到
There is a comprehensive index of temperature and humidity called damp heat index
溫度濕度有綜合的一個叫做濕熱指標
OK
OK
But what about the humidity index?
可是這個濕熱指標呢
In fact, it's just looking at everyone's thermal comfort.
其實只是在看大家的熱舒適度
It's called Somal Comfort
叫做Somal Comfort
It's whether you are comfortable or not
就是你舒不舒服
It is based on a questionnaire
它是用問卷調查出來的
so just ask you
所以就是問你說
you are in this environment
你在這個環境條件之下
Is your work efficiency good?
你這個工作效率好不好啊
Are you in a good mood? Wait a minute
你心情好不好啊等等的
It doesn't really ask us now
它其實沒有真正問到我們現在
most concerned about climate change
氣候變遷之下最關心的
Somal Stress is heat pressure
就是熱壓力Somal Stress
heat hazard
就是熱危害
It's just my body index is fast
就是我身體指標快
It's just the heart beating
就是心臟一直蹦蹦跳
I'm dying
我快不行了
I'm about to pour that before
我快要倒了那個之前
do i want to prevent this
我希望預防這個情況嘛
not if i'm in a good mood
而不是我心情好不好
or something uncomfortable
或是舒不舒服的一些事情
So Somal is
所以Somal就是
For comfort and heat stress
適合舒適度跟熱壓力
Thermal hazards are a different concept
熱危害是不一樣的概念
So what about public health?
所以在公共衛生上呢
In fact, there are more suitable
其實有比較合適的
of public health
屬於公共衛生的
The heat hazard index
這個熱危害指數
OK then we all know
OK 那我們大家就清楚
if in
如果在
If it is windy this summer
這個夏天的時候如果有風的話
wow so comfortable
哇 好舒服喔
so there is a lot of wind
所以有沒有風差很多
So wind speed is another factor to consider
所以風速是另外一個要考慮的因素
Therefore, in addition to temperature and humidity, wind speed is very important
所以除了溫度濕度之外風速很重要
one more
再一個
You see that girl breaks up in summer
你看那個女孩子夏天都打散
On the one hand, I am afraid of getting sunburned.
一方面是怕曬黑啦
On the other hand, each umbrella has a shadow
二方面的話其實一個一把傘有個陰影
not exposed to direct sunlight
沒有被太陽直射
we are much more comfortable
我們就舒服很多
So in fact by the sun
所以事實上被太陽
Is it solar radiation from direct sunlight
是不是被太陽直射的太陽輻射
It actually affects our own heat
事實上也影響我們自己的熱
this symptom of this body
這個身體的這個症狀
It is clear
很明顯
So temperature and humidity
所以溫度濕度
wind speed and solar radiation
風速跟太陽輻射
All four factors are important
這四個這個因子都重要
That
那
There is actually such an index in public health
公共衛生上其實有這樣子的指數存在
It's called the neutralization temperature heat index
它叫做中和溫度熱指數
The solution is called WBGT
解成叫做WBGT
It is to consider these four
它就是考量這四個
this indicator
這個指標
Then this WBGT is actually in public health
那這個WBGT其實在公共衛生上
In the case of labor
在勞工的場合
Labor safety and health has already been used
勞工安全衛生上面已經用了
seventy years
七十年
His early years were developed by the United States Marine Corps
他早年是美國海軍陸戰隊所發展出來的
He noticed that when the soldiers were practicing
他是注意到軍人在操練的時候
or in a submarine
或者是在潛水艇裡面
In the case of high temperature and sweltering heat close to the boiler
又高溫又悶熱接近鍋爐的情況之下
They use the physiological response of soldiers
他們就是用軍人的生理反應
Classify it like this
定出來這樣子分類
The most serious is WBGT above 32.2
最嚴重的是WBGT是32.2以上
is black flag
是黑旗
The black flag indicates that the company's soldiers are physically strong
黑旗表示連軍人身強體格
No able-bodied soldier should be in that situation
體格強健的軍人都不應該在那樣情況之下
prolonged exposure to the sun
被長久的曝曬
or prolonged exercise
或者是長久的運動
So this is the black flag
所以這個是黑旗
After these five categories are also used in
這五類之後也是用在
On the Classification of Occupational Safety and Health in the World
全世界的勞工安全衛生的分類上
someone mentioned
有人就提到說
Both soldiers and labor friends are in good shape
軍人跟勞工朋友都身強體狀的
Are their indicators suitable for ordinary people?
他們指標適不適合用在一般人
Therefore, some domestic scholars have also studied
所以國內也有學者研究出來
Indeed, from the health insurance database
確實從健保資料庫來看的話
Mortality rate of all causes of death in Taiwan
台灣地區全死因的死亡率
Significant increase above WBGT35°
在WBGT35度以上是明顯的增加
In terms of the total rescue rate
就這個總救診率來講
Significant increase above WBGT33 degrees
在WBGT33度以上是明顯的增加
WBGT actually uses cost as its standard
WBGT它其實也是用度作為它的標準
Because it is actually three
因為它其實就是三個
It is the wet bulb temperature, the black bulb temperature and the air temperature are the sum of degrees
就是濕球溫度 黑球溫度跟氣溫都是度加起來的
it has a weight added to each other
它是有一個彼此中有權重加起來的
We also talked with Mr. Tang Jingsheng from the Department of Public Health of Fuzhou University
我們也跟福大公衛系的唐靖聖老師
I also read that it is suitable for the general public
也在看說那適合一般民眾
Is that suitable for the elderly?
那適不適合老人家呢
So Mr. Tang here
所以唐老師這邊
healthy elderly
就招呼了健康老年人
Then let's compare WBGT with other evil indexes that we are familiar with
然後來比較一下WBGT跟我們熟知的其他的失惡指數
Let's talk about these for the elderly
來看說這些對老人家來講
Which is the most appropriate indicator of harm
哪一個是最合適的認為害指標
After comparison, it is still WBGT
比較起來之後還是WBGT
So to show this WBGT it can actually be shown to the general public
所以顯示這個WBGT它其實是可以示在一般民眾
What's more, it is suitable for the sensitive group that is the most important to this heat hazard
更何況是適合用在對這個熱危害最重要的這個敏感的這個族群
is the old man
就是老人家
So we know that with WBGT
所以我們知道用WBGT
So if we are indoors
所以我們在家戶室內的話
We use WBGT to measure
我們就用WBGT做測量
The luminosity we measured, etc.
我們測的那些光度等等
In the end, it is converted into the index of WBGT
到最後都轉換成WBGT這個指數
Then our total
然後我們這個總共
Its practical questionnaire has interviewed more than 2,000 households
其實用問卷訪問有2000多個家戶
But we have limited equipment
可是我們因為儀器有限
So only more than 500 households accept our indoor testing
所以只有500多個家戶接受我們的這個室內的檢測
Then the last data is exactly 500
那最後有下數據剛好是500個
What about the middle 500?
那這500個中間呢
There is this 20% and the other 36%
有這個20%個跟另外36%個
5% of the total are red flags and black flags
佔總數的5%是屬於紅旗跟黑旗的
OK
OK
The words of the red flag mean that the community with a sense of co-branding is likely to pay attention
紅旗的話就表示聯名感社群很可能都要注意
it shouldn't stay in that environment for too long
它不應該待在那樣環境中太久
So in total there are 26 households
所以總共的話有26個家戶
What about the 26 households?
那這26個家戶呢
it this game is black flag family
它這個遊戲是黑旗家戶
it is
它是
The temperature in the room, if they have a thermometer in the house
室內的溫度,如果他們家有溫度計的話
The indoor temperature has actually reached more than 4 billion
室內的溫度其實也已經到達40億以上
So they actually know just by looking at the thermometer
所以他們其實光看溫度計都知道說
They should do some adjustments
他們應該要做一些調適作用
whether it's going out for a walk
不管是出去走走
We actually had
我們其實之前有
One of the grandmothers, their house is really often more than 40 degrees
其中一個阿嬤,他們家真的是常常40幾度
His home is Xishai, ok
他家是溪曬,ok
then we say
然後我們就說
Let's just say that the temperature in your era is too high
我們就說你這個時代溫度太高了
So if you usually say, is it when you are drying in the stream
所以你平常的話,是不是在溪曬的時候
What do you do, do you often drink water?
你是做什麼樣,是常常喝水嗎
how about washing your face
洗臉嗎,怎麼樣
He still laughs at us, ok
他還笑我們,ok
He laughed and said, I'm not that stupid
他笑說,其實我沒有那麼笨啊
He said that when the temperature reaches 40 degrees, I will
他說真的到40度的時候我就
Hiding out, I hid in a nearby hypermarket
躲出去了啦,我就躲到附近的大賣場
Blow off the air conditioner
吹冷氣去了
ok, but luckily the old grandma is nearby
ok,可是還好這老阿嬤附近
There is a hypermarket within 15 minutes of this walk
這個走15分鐘之內是有大賣場的
So if people in remote areas probably don't have
那如果偏遠地區的民眾很可能沒有
Then he has nowhere to hide
那他也沒有地方躲
ok so there are a lot of these
ok,所以這些很多
Well, if two of them don't have air-conditioning at all
這個,其中的話有兩個人根本就沒有冷氣的
this device
這個設備
Other words are reluctant or do not need to open
其他的話是捨不得或是不需要開
Nine people thought that the temperature at that time was not bad, just right
有九個人是覺得當時的溫度還好啦 剛好
if he really has hot room sex
如果他真的有熱室性的話
it's okay
也就還好了
But what we're afraid of is that he doesn't feel it himself.
可是我們怕的是他自己沒有感覺
Because like some old people, he is old after all
因為像有些老人家他畢竟這個年紀大了
He feels a little slower
他的感覺比較稍微遲緩一些
what is afraid is what is said
那怕的是擔心的是說
It's too late when they feel this discomfort
他們感覺到這個不舒服的時候已經來不及了
OK
OK
So for these households
那所以針對這些家戶
In fact, all the more than 500 households
其實所有的500多個家戶
We'll all be based on the condition of his room
我們都會根據他室內的狀況
Will give a feedback at the end
到最後都會給一個回饋意見
Just suggest that they can be in the summer
就是建議他們可以在夏天的時候
what to do when it's hot
很熱的時候可以做一些什麼樣的
accommodating behavior
等於說是調適的行為
including air conditioning
包括開冷氣
then drink more water
然後多喝水
And actually there is a meaning to tell us
而且其實有個意思也告訴我們
not just drink more water
不只是多喝水
It is better to drink more jelly or jade
最好是多喝仙草或是礙玉
He said it's because it's a jelly-like jelly
他說因為這種是膠狀的膠質
So drink the water in the stomach sometimes
所以在肚子裡面的水喝下去有的時候
If you just rush out, it will make you electrolytically swell
就衝出去的反而是讓你電解脹
unbalanced
不平衡
What if it's Aiyu or this fairy grass?
那如果是愛玉或者是這個仙草類的呢
He was frozen in the frontier
他就在未領節凍
After the festival, he will discharge it slowly
節了之後呢他再慢慢排出去
So it's better for our body
所以對我們身體是比較好的
OK
OK
So we all gave him these opinions
所以我們都有給他這些意見
hope is good for them
希望是對他們是有好處
Then we also put these relevant information
那我們也把這些相關的資訊的話
also gave this
也都給了這個
The Social Welfare Department of the Ministry of Health and Welfare is a reference
這個衛福部的這個社家署參考
ok so we're indoors
好 所以我們是在家戶室內
There are tests like this
有做這樣子的檢測
Then we are also in the community
那我們也在社區內
OK
OK
We put this quarantine room
我們放了這個檢疫室的
This meteorological observation instrument with solar cold plate
有太陽冷板的這個氣象觀測儀器
Measure the temperature of these greenhouses
測量這些溫室度
Wind speed, solar radiation, etc.
風速啊太陽輻射這些資料
Then these words are spread infinitely
那這些的話也無限傳出
Integrate with our partners
整合到我們的合作的夥伴
Go to this network platform of Mr. Chen Fangzhang of this information center
這個資訊所陳方章老師的這個網路平台裡面去
that these this
那這些的這個
Actual measurements in the community
在社區的實際測量
we are actually
我們其實是
specially placed
特意放在
Everyone will walk and pass
大家會走路會經過的
Like asphalt road, red brick road
像柏油路啦 紅磚路啦
or on the cobblestone road
或者是石板路上
Because that's what everyone actually does every day
因為那個是大家實際上每天會
This situation of thermal hazards actually received
實際上接受到的熱危害的這個情況
Then everyone knows how the Meteorological Bureau measures since they were young, right?
那大家從小都知道氣象局是怎麼測的對不對
The standard test is a white house in the middle of the grass
標準的測戰是草地上中間一個白房子
Baiye Township. The inside of Baiye Township should not be exposed to direct sunlight.
百葉鄉百葉鄉裡面還不能太陽直射
But when we are outside, we are directly exposed to the sun.
可是我們人在外面就是被太陽直射
Below us is the asphalt road.
我們底下就是柏油路啊
So what is the purpose of the weather bureau testing him?
所以氣象局測戰他的目的呢
not for going
並不是為了要去
uh measure our heat hazard
呃測量我們的熱危害
He is here to say
他是為了說在這個地的
Meteorological data should be able to be used as a reference with other countries
氣象資料要能夠跟別國的去做參考
So they must have a standard measurement method
所以他們必須要一個標準的一個測量方式
But this standard measurement method is not suitable for us to measure this thermal hazard
可是這個標準的測量方式並不適合我們去測量這個熱危害
So we are in each
所以我們在每個
The words of the community are actually measuring their actual thermal hazard
社區的話是實際上測量他們實際的熱危害
that traditionally
那在傳統上
uh industry
呃工業
It should be said that public health
應該說公共衛生上
We measure thermal hazard
我們測量熱危害的
this
這個
The instrument used is actually this one
用的儀器呢其實是這台
Well we're going to call him a gauge for WBGT
好我們就要叫他做WBGT的測量儀
If this station
這台的話
he has a black ball temperature
他有一個黑球溫度
This is very important and related to radiation measurement.
這個是非常重要的叫測輻射的相關的
Now some meteorological units in various countries in the world already know the parameter of WBGT
現在世界各國有些氣象單位已經知道WBGT這個參數
But they haven't been able to put WBGT into the program, which they think is harmful to the index.
可是他們還沒有辦法把WBGT放成是他們認為害指數的這個
Within this early warning system
這個預警的這個系統之內
The main reason is that these standard meteorological conditions around the world
最主要是因為現在全世界的這些標準的氣象
Meteorological parameters measured Meteorological parameters
氣象參數測量出來氣象參數
There is no way to convert it into this black ball temperature
沒辦法轉化成這個黑球溫度
There is no way to convert it into black ball temperature
沒辦法轉化成黑球溫度
So you can't use the WBGT classification we just talked about
所以就不能夠用我們剛剛講WBGT的分級來做
There is a final reasoning in the middle
這個中間是有一個最後一理路
Our team tried to find a way to connect the last line of reasoning
我們團隊想辦法把最後一理路連結起來
We also checked the literature
我們也查了文獻
In fact, there are already many
其實文獻上早就有很多
It should be said that there are several articles
應該說是好幾篇
Use meteorological instruments and WBGT to do this comparison in a certain place
用氣象儀器跟WBGT在某一個地方去做這個比對
Then do this experience room
然後做的這個經驗室
But this experience room can often be used in Japan, but it cannot
可是這個經驗室常常是能夠用在日本的就不能
not available in Taiwan
不能用在台灣
Why is Japanese?
因為日本的話比較乾嘛
It is very different in this environment
它就這個環境條件很不一樣
OK
OK
So it is subject to local restrictions
所以就是會受到地方上的限制
Fortunately, we found one
那還好我們有找到一篇
is in the literature is a national laboratory of the United States
是在文獻中是美國的國家實驗室
it made
它做出來
It is a way of theoretically deriving heat transfer
它是用理論推導熱力傳輸的這個方式
Deduced
推導出
In the end our meteorological parameters
到底我們這些氣象參數
How to convert to WBGT
怎麼樣轉化成WBGT
But what about the transformation of this?
那不過這個的這個轉化呢
It has only been tested at five locations in the US
它只有在美國五個地方測試過
Not tested anywhere else
其他地方都沒有測試
It's like Taiwan's high temperature and high humidity
那像台灣高溫高濕
So we also have to come to Taiwan to test
所以我們也必須要來台灣測試
so we are in taiwan
所以我們就在台灣
in this North Central South
在這個北中南
At least ten communities were tested before and after
前後後大概測了至少十個社區
different types of communities
就是不同型態的社區
ok then we are
好 那我們就是
In this use the meteorological parameters just now
在這個用剛剛的氣象參數
After measuring the meteorological parameters, it is transformed into this theoretical room
測了氣象參數之後轉化成這個理論室
we get a
我們得到一個
The estimated value of this routine observation
這個例行的觀測的估算值
OK
OK
Then compare it to WBGT
然後把它跟WBGT
This instrument traditionally
這個儀器傳統
Compare with the instrument actually used in public health
跟公共衛生上實際上用的這個儀器來做比較
Everyone can take a look
大家可以看一下
In fact, the correlation is very good
其實相關性非常好
0.99 then its synergy is 1
0.99然後它的協力是1
We have accumulated more than 3000 records
我們已經累計了3000多筆資料
ok
ok
After getting this information
那得到這個資料之後
of course we are happy
我們當然很高興
Then I went to my senior from the Meteorological Bureau and said
然後我就去找我這個氣象局的學長說
Hey senior, it can be used now, right?
欸學長這下子可以用了吧
You see we continue to do so well in Taiwan
你看我們在台灣就繼續做這麼好
So you can use this WBGT as the indicator of the stomach damage index, right?
所以你可以用這WBGT作為肉胃害指數的這個指標了吧
He said hey girl
他說欸學妹啊
You have studied meteorology for so long
你學氣象學這麼久
do not you know
你不知道嗎
The weather bureau's most important thing is the forecast
氣象局最重要的是預報啦
what you can't predict
你不能預報的話
so I'm useless
所以我都都都沒有用
You told me that your measured values ​​are very close
你告訴我說你實測值很接近
It's useless
其實沒有用
To be accurate
要預報準才行
good
好
So we spent a lot of effort
所以我們又很花了很多功夫
I will find teacher Lin Chuanyao from our center
我就找我們中心的林川瑤老師
He also has a forecast mode
他也是有一個預報模式
I am looking for Dr. Hong Yingshan, my classmate from the Meteorological Bureau
我找我氣象局的這個同學洪穎山博士
Then he himself has the model used by the Meteorological Bureau
然後他自己也是有這個氣象局用的模式
private weather company
還有民間的氣象公司
They are also very interested in our WBGT
他們也對我們這個WBGT很有興趣
They are also willing to initiate
他們也願意主動啟動
give us a forecast
給我們的預報
So we have three different patterns
所以我們有三種不同的模式
But the data we've presented so far is one of those patterns
但我們目前呈現的資料是其中一種模式
we are
我們是
Their model data predictions give me
他們模式的資料預測給我
It is forecasting 48 hours data to me
是預測48小時資料給我
Then we tested locally
然後我們在當地實測了
After WBGT
WBGT之後
Let's compare it with his model
我們再去跟他的模式做比對
In fact, compared
其實比對出來
In fact, the correlation is quite high
其實相關性蠻高的
0.94
0.94
words from our WI
我們的WI的話
For example, it is 0.98
寫例的話是0.98
is also very good
也是非常好
so i think
所以我是覺得
In the future, we will continue to discuss with the Meteorological Bureau
未來我們還是繼續會跟氣象局在談
That is to say, we can actually use existing models to make forecasts
就是說我們其實已經可以用現有的模式來進行預報
Of course I know the weather bureau is more cautious
當然我知道氣象局是比較謹慎
It needs to have accumulated enough data
它需要有累積到足夠的數據
we are now too
我們現在也是
provides a lot of information
提供了很多的資料
The proof hopefully will convince it
所證的希望能夠說服它
So this is in the schema section
所以這個是在模式這個部分
We test in the community
我們在社區實測
just mentioned
剛提到
We can use the local meteorological survey
我們可以用氣象局當地的測佔
to convert
去換算出
His local survey
他當地測佔
In this view the harm index WBGT
在這個認為害指數WBGT
We also do measurements at altitude
我們也在高度層有做測量
more than three floors
三層樓以上
We have a thin trail above the ground
我們有在地面層薄幼路上面
Or do it on the red brick road
或者是這個紅磚道上面做
then we can take a look
那我們可以看一下
In fact, this WBGT
其實這個WBGT
the ground layer that we humans actually walk on
我們人所實際上走的地面層
It is on average better than
它平均來講都要比
WBGT of nearby Meteorological Bureau stations
附近的氣象局測站的WBGT
1.5 degrees higher on average
平均要高1.5度
OK
OK
But correlation is good
不過相關是滿好的
0.7
0.7
So I also talked to Qishang School
所以我也是跟七上學講說
In the future, if you predict
以後你們如果預報的話
In fact, at least our
其實至少我們這個
70% of this
就是有70%的這個
Credibility
可信度
that is
就是說
you just said you can believe it
你剛才是說可以相信它
then we are here with you
那我們在你這個
We only need to take this data from your forecast
我們只要把你預報的這個數據
because it predicts
因為它預報出去
It's probably data from weather stations.
大概都是氣象測站這樣子的數據
We add 1.5 degrees C
我們再加上1.5度C
Basically we are walking on a normal thin path
基本上就是我們走在一般的薄幼路上面
say actual heat hazard
說實際上的熱危害
That'll be fine
這樣就行了
Take a look, the maximum value we measured on the ground floor is actually as high as 41
大家看一下,我們在地面層所測到的最大值其實會高達41
We are already in the black period just on 32.2
我們剛剛32.2就已經是黑期了
But we actually measured it to be 41
可是我們實際上這個是測出來會是41
Of course no one will walk on Boyue Road for 8 hours
當然沒有人會在博越路上一直走走走8小時
I hope not, so I hope no one will keep saying
希望沒有啦,所以希望不會有人一直持續說
Spit into such a large high value
吐入到這麼大的高值
We are actually estimating, and we use this to calculate
我們實際也在估算,就是用這個去計算
This Taipei City, because Taipei City is a basin
這個台北市,因為台北市是盆地
It is easier to gather heat and not easy to dissipate
比較容易聚熱不容易散出去
Therefore, Taipei City is usually the place with the highest temperature in Taiwan.
所以台北市通常都是整個台灣溫度最高的地方
It’s not that Kaohsiung is quite windy, so it’s actually Taipei
不是高雄風還蠻大的,所以事實上是台北
So we look at Taipei City from 2002 to 2016
所以我們看台北市從2002年到2016年
In the past 15 years, the maximum value of WBGT on the same day exceeded 32.2 days
這15年間,當天WBGT最大值超過32.2天數
How many days?
有多少天呢?
more than 1000 days
1000多天
OK
OK
it is in the summer half
它是在夏天半年
Let us suppose
我們假設
I think Taiwan is now only tantamount to saying
我覺得台灣現在只有等於說
Two seasons of winter
下冬兩個季節了
In fact, even winter is full of heat
其實連冬天都是滿熱的
Summer half year is from May to October
夏半年就是5到10月
If we only count the half year
如果我們只算這半年的話
It actually accounted for 37% of the more than 1,000 days
它這1000多天其實占了37%
it's impressive
這是很可觀
means to say
表示就是說
throughout the second half of the year
整個的下半年中間
more than a third of the time
有三分之一上的時間的話
In fact, every day exceeds this
其實每天都會超出這個
We consider thermal hazards
我們認為熱危害
more severe days
比較嚴重的天數
then such a situation
那這樣的情況
among us feel
我們當中覺得
If there is timely warning data
如果說能夠有及時預警的資料
how good is it
有多好呢
like this
這樣子的話
people will know
民眾就會知道說
it's too hot outside now
現在外面太熱了
I don't want to go out
我不要出去了
or me the athlete
或者是我這個運動員
half training says
訓練到一半說
we better come back now
我們現在還是回來好了
don't train outside
不要在外面訓練
But because now the Meteorological Bureau
但是因為現在氣象局
Even if we convert his kitchen
即使我們把他的餐廚做轉換了
But the Meteorological Bureau is now on the Internet
可是氣象局現在在網路
this timely
這個及時
Timely data on the website
網站上的及時數據
With temperature, humidity and wind speed
有溫度、濕度跟風速
But it doesn't have this timely
可是呢 它沒有這個及時的
Information about solar radiation
太陽輻射的資料
OK so
OK 所以
Our dating house
我們這個都約院
Our team is in the whole province
我們這個團隊呢 就在全省
From this 2016
從這個2016年開始
It has been established since last year
去年開始 就設了
15 successively established
陸陸續續設了15個
Outdoor Seven Observatory
室外的七項觀測站
OK we just want to put this
OK 我們就是希望把這個
Radiation data can be disseminated in time
輻射的資料能夠及時傳出出來
Then we can calculate
然後我們就可以計算
This WBGT in time
及時的這個WBGT
OK last year it was
OK 去年的話是
hottest year hottest year ever
最熱的一年 歷史上最熱的一年
In Taiwan, it is
在台灣來講的話 就
If WBGT is calculated, it is July
計算WBGT的話 是7月
This is when the WBG is the highest
是這個WBG最高的時候
that july
那7月
July 28 is the highest day of WBG
7月28號那天是WBG最高
OK, let's see for a couple of days
OK 那我們來看一下 這兩天
The whole month of July last year followed
這個去年7月一整個月跟
This July 28th
這個7月28號那天
This WBG distribution map
這個WBG分布圖
Our calculations are based on 12 hours in the daytime.
我們這個都是以白天12個小時來計算
The one on the left is the average of 12 hours of daylight in the whole month of July
那左邊這個的話是7月全月的白天12小時的平均
Then we also see that there are a few black spots here
那我們也看到有幾個黑點在這裡
ok Momotsuki wait for this
ok 桃月那等這個
Those two black dots
那這兩個黑點的話
It's still going on for a whole month
在一整個月居然都還會
This average is as high as 32.2
這個平均值高達32.2
So these two are probably due to the terrain
所以這兩個很可能是因為地形的關係
The wind speed is relatively low or this
風速比較低啦或者是這個
Factors such as relatively high rock and soil will cause this
石土比較高等等的因素會造成這樣子
This is actually a social welfare unit or a labor unit.
這個其實是社福單位或者是勞工單位
The key point to pay attention to in the future
以後需要注意的這個的重點
that was on july 28th
那在7月28號的時候
Full water has more can daytime 12 hour average
全水有更多的可以當天白天12小時平均值
Belong to this more than 32.2
是屬於這個32.2以上的更多
ok, that part of Taoyuan, Taozhuniao
ok 那桃園啊桃豬鳥這個部分
Then the following words are this
然後底下的話是這個
Kaohsiung and Pingtung also have some
高雄屏東也有一些
The thing that surprised me the most was actually
那其實最讓我吃驚的其實是
first place ok first place
第一名ok 第一名
Obviously it is Yonghe District in New Taipei City
明明居然是新北市的永和區
OK
OK
Because I myself grew up forever
因為我自己是永和長大的
i can't believe our yong ho will win the championship
我不敢相信我們的永和會拿冠軍
It's actually 33.5 degrees during the day
居然是白天會到33.5度
after i know this
我知道這個之後呢
I will tell my mother
我就跟我媽媽講
Because my mother is in the group that does not turn on the air conditioner at home
因為我媽媽在家裡是不開冷氣的那一組的
Because she also thinks she is used to it
因為她也是覺得她習慣了
She washes her face and it's fine
她洗洗臉這樣就好了
So I just told her please please later
所以我就跟她講說拜託拜託你以後
We have already won the first place in the province in this matter.
這個 這個事我們已經拿全省第一了
OK, in the future, you must turn on the air conditioner, what do you want?
OK 以後的話一定要開冷氣一定要怎麼樣
Fortunately, she believed me this year
還好她今年相信我了
This year, at 12:00 noon every day
她今年的話每天中午12點的時候
she will drive for an hour
她都會開一個小時
then tell me it's nice
然後跟我講說很不錯
One hour can measure four hours
開一個小時可以量四個小時
OK
OK
So at least I don't have to worry about her this year.
所以至少的話今年不用擔心她
but this
但是這個
Converting this WBGT has this benefit
換算這個WBGT有這個好處
just to help us figure out where it's going to fall
就是幫我們找出哪些地方會墜落
So this labor unit or social welfare unit
所以這個勞工單位或者是社福單位
can focus on these villages
可以聚焦在這些的這個村裡
Okay, when we were drawing this picture
好 我們在畫這個圖的時候呢
Actually we still have this
其實我們還有這個
adjusted in some scientific way
用一些科學的方式來調整了
to correct this
來校正了這個
heat island effect
各地的熱島效應
We all know that in the city because of the relationship between the buildings
我們都知道都市裡面因為建築物的關係
So it creates this heat island effect
所以會造成這個熱島效應
That is to say, cement and thin oil cannot dissipate after absorbing heat
就是說水泥 薄油 吸熱之後散不出去
So it's going to be warmer than the usual suburbs next to the suburbs
所以它會比平常的郊區 旁邊的郊區溫度要高
So we're using the government's numerical terrain model
所以我們就是利用政府的數值地形模型
We built the three-dimensional volume of the building with a five-meter resolution
我們就建置了這個五公尺解析度的建物的三維量體
Think of it as a three-dimensional urbanization indicator
把它當作是一個三維的都市化的指標
This three-dimensional urbanization index we also go to
這個三維都市化指標我們也去
Take that and compare it to the temperature distribution on satellite imagery
把它拿去跟衛星影像上的溫度分布
In addition, there are more than 30 measuring stations of the Meteorological Bureau in Taipei City.
還有就是在台北市比較密集有三十幾個氣象局的測站
its ground station
它的地面測站
Then do the correlation
然後來做相關性
Its correlation is very high
它的相關性都非常高
Therefore, the three-dimensional urbanization index is also a good indicator to look at the temperature distribution.
所以三維都市化指標也是一個很好的看溫度分布的指標
But I built another biggest purpose is to
但是我建置另外一個最大的用意就是
I hope it's for urban planners to see
我希望是讓都市規劃的人看到
So if everyone here
所以如果在座各位
If someone is doing urban planning
有人是做都市規劃的話
Because always prevent residual treatment
因為永遠是預防剩餘治療
OK, we're still working hard to build a house
OK 我們還在拼命的蓋房子
And it's covered with cement
而且是蓋這個水泥
This house is reinforced concrete
這個房子 鋼筋水泥
So every house built
所以每蓋一棟房子
In fact we just add this
事實上我們就是增加這個
The volume of this three-dimensional building
這個三維的建物的量體
Unless they can find some heat sink
除非他們可以找一些吸熱
compare this
比較這個
The materials of these buildings that are not so tall
不那麼高的這些建築的材料
Otherwise they are all increasing our thermal conductivity
否則他們都是在增加我們的熱導效應
and adding weight to this under our climate change
然後增加重了我們氣候變遷之下的這個
warming shock
增溫的衝擊
OK
OK
So I think this thing should be reminded of this
所以我覺得這個事要提醒這個
urban planner
都市規劃的人
OK, let's take a look again.
好 那我們再看一下就是
In fact, everyone feels that the weather is very hot this time.
這期天氣其實大家都覺得很熱
OK
OK
so this was a few days ago
所以這個是幾天前
Last week, July 19th
上個禮拜七月十九號
12:00 noon to 1:00 pm
中午十二點到下午一點
this hour
這一個小時的
Let's take back the temperature from the weather bureau
我們把氣象局的溫度拿回來看
its geographical distribution
這個它的地理分布
Then we also use our
然後我們也用我們
Traditional Radiation Information
傳統的輻射資料
We ourselves use
我們自己也是利用
The Meteorological Bureau has a total of more than 300 stations for temperature, humidity and wind speed
氣象局總共有三百多個站的溫度濕度跟風速
plus our own radiation data
再加上我們自己的輻射資料
We can quickly calculate this WBGT
我們就可以很快去算這個WBGT
We can look at its distribution
我們可以看看它的分布
Indeed something is different
確實有些是不一樣
Especially in some of the more important hotspot areas
尤其是在一些比較重要的熱點的區域
WBGT because it considers more
WBGT因為它考量比較多
And the more important parameters related to physiology
而且比較重要的跟生理有關的參數
So it can identify more detailed
所以它可以identify更細緻的
Some important black spots
一些比較重要的黑點
black area
黑區
These exceed WBGT
這些超過WBGT
These areas are beyond the black area
這些區域都是超過黑起區
This is our afterthought
這個是我們事後
The data is recovered and drawn with GIS
資料收回來用GIS在畫的
The best paintings are those that can be drawn in time
最好的畫是能夠及時
Now we are also cooperating with Teacher Chen from the Information Office
現在我們也是跟資訊所的陳老師合作
We are available online in real time
我們是可以及時的在網路上
First present these temperature data from the Meteorological Bureau
先呈現氣象局的這些溫度資料
And the temperature data of our own 15 stations
還有我們自己的15個站的溫度資料
and add it to our radiation profile
然後再把它加上我們的輻射資料
Convert to WBGT
轉化成WBGT
So this is the data at 1:30 pm on July 20
所以這個是7月20號下午1點半的資料
You can see many places
大家可以看到很多地方
In fact, many places in the western half are black chess
其實西半部很多地方都是黑棋
There is only one area in the middle
那只有中間有一塊地區的
It's because of the cloud and the relatively strong wind speed.
是因為有雲以及風速比較大的關係
So the temperature drops faster
所以就是降溫降得比較快
The north side too
那北部這邊也是
On the Danshui side, because the wind blows
淡水這邊的話因為有風吹
So it goes down faster
所以降得比較快
What about the black chess
那這個黑棋的情況
lasts until 4 p.m.
一直持續到下午4點
OK, it lasted so long
OK,有持續的這麼久
OK, so in fact we're observing this immediate
好,所以事實上我們在觀察這個即時的
Sometimes it is found that there is a thermal hazard
熱危害的時候有發現有的時候
Black's words will continue until 6:00 p.m.
黑棋的話一直會持續到下午6點
OK, this is
OK,這個是
especially in this
尤其是在這個
Special attention should be paid to those who work outside the office
事外作業的人的話是要特別的注意
then we also want
那我們也想
In the future, we can cooperate with the Meteorological Bureau in this regard.
未來的話可以跟氣象局在這方面合作
be able to take the data we've built
能夠把我們所建置的這些資料
available to the Bureau of Meteorology
都能夠提供給氣象局
This WBGT warning can be issued in the future
未來可以發佈這個WBGT的預警
with this instant observation
跟這個即時的觀測
Currently the Taipei City Environmental Protection Bureau is very interested in
目前台北市環保局是非常有興趣
We are currently cooperating with the Taipei City Environmental Protection Bureau
目前我們在跟台北市環保局合作
It is hoped that the system of Relujing in Taipei City can be established
希望能夠建置台北市熱律景的制度
So let's look at that day
所以我們來看一下那一天
At 1:30 p.m. on July 21
7月21號下午1點半的時候
The whole city of Taipei is black
整個台北市全部都是黑的
Because Taipei City is not easy to dissipate heat
因為台北市本來就不容易散熱
is a basin center
是個盆地地心
Only Yangmingshan is slightly more comfortable
只有陽明山是稍微是比較舒爽一點
Look at the white in the middle
大家看一下這中間的白色
says it has no data
表示它沒有資料
Because we follow the weather station
因為我們是按照氣象站
Draw a circle if its diameter is within 5 kilometers
方圓它的直徑5公里之內的話畫一個圓
So there are missing values ​​in some places
所以有些地方是有缺漏值的
In the future, we hope that
未來的話我們希望也可以
Real-time prediction of thermal hazards for the Taipei area
為台北地區來做熱危害的即時預計
Currently cooperating with Taipei Environmental Protection Bureau
目前跟台北市環保局合作
In fact, we are on top of the earth lock of Academia Sinica
其實我們在中研院的地球鎖頂上
There is a weather station that we set up
就有一個我們設的氣象站
We originally wanted to set it up on the roof of the Japan Ministry
當初我們本來想設在日本部樓頂
However, there are too many outlets of air conditioners on the roof of the Japanese department, which will affect our data
可是日本部樓頂的冷氣機出口太多會影響到我們的數據
So it was not set there
所以後來就沒有設在那邊
We are in Taipei except for the stop of Zhongyingyuan
我們在台北市除了中營院這一站之外
We also have four other stations
我們還有設另外其他四個站
It was done for the Taipei City Environmental Protection Bureau
那是為了台北市環保局做的
So we also analyzed the historical data of Taipei City
所以我們也分析了台北市的歷史資料
last 15 years
過去15年間
If we only look at May to October
如果我們只看5到10月的話
We look at the highest WBGT of the United States and Japan
我們看美日的最高WBGT
On which level of thermal hazard would it be distributed
它會分佈在熱危害的哪一個等級
From the perspective of 2016
以2016年來看的話
There are actually 103 days
居然有103天
It's more than half the time it's on black paint
就是一半以上的時間它是落在黑漆的
this is serious
這個是蠻嚴重的
So everyone don't want to say
所以大家不要想說
What price can be placed above 32.2 degrees
32.2度以上可以放什麼價
it's impossible
這是不可能的事
Because this is the norm for us
因為我們這個已經是常態了
But we can indeed remind you
但是我們確實是可以提醒大家
at this time
就是在這個時候
For example, children should not go outside
譬如說小孩子不要在外面
Or athletes marked outside training
或是運動員標在外面訓練
or how outdoor workers protect themselves
或者是室外工作者怎麼樣保護他們自己
If we take this
如果我們是以這個
The 99th percentile of the daily maximum temperature for the past 15 years
每日最高溫過去這15年來的99%分位數
That is 36.8%
那個就是36.8%
If used as another level of classification
如果作為另外一級的分級的話
we are one more level
我們就多了一級
The hottest year in 2016 last year
在2016年去年最熱烈的這一年
about 5 days
大概會有5天
would be this higher than this 36.8%
會是這個高於這個36.8%的
so it's possible
所以這有可能
We are still discussing with the Taipei City Environmental Protection Bureau
我們正在還在跟台北市環保局在商量
say it's possible
說這有可能是不是
if you really want to post this
如果真的要發佈這個
In other words, I suggest that everyone should not go out.
比較說建議大家都不要外出的話
It is possible that the relatively high temperature
是可能是以比較高溫的這個
as this pre-value
來作為這個預先值
Of course such discussions
當然這樣的討論
There's a lot behind this
還有很多的背後的這個
science we have to try our best
科學我們要盡量的去進行
including our statistics institute
包括我們在跟我們統計所
Teacher Huang Jingxiang is cooperating
黃景祥老師在合作
just look at this
就是看說這個
Use health insurance data to analyze
用健保資料過來分析
this some health
這個一些健康
healthy data
健康的這個資料
We based on the past 2000 to 2014
我們根據過去2000年到2014年
Including the number of emergency visits, the number of old visits or
包括是急診數 舊診數 或者是
The number of deaths after 2008 The number of deaths from all causes
2008年之後這個死亡人數 全死因的死亡人數
We can currently see about 32.5 degrees or more
我們目前都可以看到大概32.5度以上
WBGT32.5 degrees or more
WBGT32.5度以上
Or above 33 degrees, it is a sharp rise
或者是33度以上 都是急劇上升
As for this part, we are still working on it.
那這個部分的話 我們還在繼續的進行
But that's pretty much it
不過還蠻就是說
The relevant information is quite consistent.
這個相關的資料都還蠻吻合的
Next, we also see another
接下來的話 我們也在看到另外一個就是
The high-risk group we just kept mentioning
我們剛剛一直提到的這個高鋪險的族群
It means working outdoors, especially construction workers
就是在室外勞工 尤其是營建工人
It is dried by this long-term shop
被長期的這個鋪曬
This is a person who works on site to block steel bars
這個是現場一個擋鋼筋的這個作業的人員
This is the Labor Safety Office of the Labor Council
這個是勞委會的勞安所
labor safety office
勞動部的勞安所
They know we're doing this outdoor WBGT
他們知道我們在做這個室外WBGT
So they also come to cooperate with us
所以他們也來跟我們合作
Then last year, we found five long-term jobs
那這個去年的話 我們找了這個五個長職
Let’s take a look at the actual process of labor that we have seen in the five long-term jobs
大家看一下就是我們在這個五個長職所看到的這個勞工實際過程
work situation
工作的情況
This one is in Banggang
這位在榜岡京
Then this word is doing this template
然後這個的話是在做這個模板
It has this cement in it
就它裡面有這個水泥
have this plank
有這個木板
These are heat-absorbing materials
這些都是吸熱的材質
ok
ok
Then this is doing electric welding
那這個的話是在做電焊
and next to it is a surfboard
然後它旁邊是有浪板
tree with surf boards reflecting sunlight
浪板反射太陽光的樹
also very dazzling very hot
也非常刺目非常熱
The electric welding is also a very hot
那電焊也是一個非常熱的
So they are in the workplace
所以他們在作業的場所中
There are a lot of things that are
有很多通通都是
within a meter of them
在他們在近距離一公尺之內
They will have accumulated high temperature
他們就會有累積高溫的
so they are exposed to thermal hazards
所以他們所近身受到了熱危害
Probably very different 10 meters away
很可能在10公尺外是很不一樣的
ok
ok
so what about this
所以這個呢
That's why Labor Bran
就是為什麼勞動布蘭所
He hopes to develop a wearable device
他希望能夠發展一個穿戴式的裝置
Therefore, Mr. Chen Yanzhi of our information center
所以我們這個資訊所的陳寗志老師
Also use a small one for them
也為他們用一個就是小型的
Sensing of miniature temperature, humidity, etc.
微型的溫度濕度等等的感測
go get a small one like an orange bag
去弄一個小型的像一個橘色袋子
Tied to this waist of labor
綁在勞動的這個腰間
so these words
所以這些的話
help us to tie this orange bag
都有幫我們去綁這個橘色的袋子
let's see
那我們看一下
like this
像這個
I admire this pre-resident worker the most
我是最佩服這位預住工人
He's going to stand on that pre-dwelling steel girder
他是要站在那個預住的鋼樑上
Because he wants to direct where the two pre-occupied pillars will fall
因為他要指揮那個預住的兩柱要掉在哪裡
Once he stood there, he couldn't get down for two or three hours.
他一站在那邊就是兩三個小時下不來
OK
OK
Then I want to say that when I went to this construction site at seven o'clock in the morning
那我自己想說我早上七點去這個工地的時候
I have already sunned into this big Hanlin
我都已經晒到這個大漢林裡了
Then he will stand there for two or three hours
那他要在那邊站兩三個小時
really hard
真的非常辛苦
The director of the construction site told us that
那工地的主任就告訴我們說
don't be afraid
不用怕啦
They are heat acclimatized
他們是有熱適應
They've been doing this for so long
他們做這個行做那麼久了
none of them matter
他們都沒有關係
That's what these laborers told us
那這些勞工也都是這樣子告訴我們
He said they were used to it
他說他們都習慣了
OK
OK
But Tian Wenjun also told us at the same time
可是他們田問軍的時侯也同時告訴我們
In fact, more than half of them have this kind of experience
其實一半的以上都有種屬的這個經驗
It's just that none of them seek medical attention
那只是他們都沒有就醫
just drink more water
只是就是多喝水
Then just rest there
然後在那邊休息就好了
OK
OK
So although these are for us
所以這些雖然對我們來講
maybe not
可能不是
This is the ethnic group with high ranks
這是高鋪銜的族群
so they may be fit and healthy
所以他們可能身強體健
not what we usually say
不是我們一般來講的
This community that seems so sensitive and fragile
好像那麼敏感脆弱的這個社群
But think about these strong and strong people
可是想想他們這些身強體壯的人
Maybe it's the spirit of the family
可能都是家庭裡面的精神
the backbone of the economy
經濟的支柱
in case of falling down
萬一倒下去的時候
Most likely a whole family is broken
很可能破碎的是一整個家庭
So the Ministry of Labor knows this very well.
所以勞動部的話也非常知道這點
So the current word is hope to say
所以目前的話就是希望說
There is this wearable this
有這種穿戴式的這個
Thermometric Hazards
測熱危害
Then the data can be transmitted to the back-end platform
然後能夠把資料傳輸到後端的平台
What about this platform?
那這個平台呢
Can let the site supervisor see
可以讓工地主任看
so they can do this time shift
所以他們就可以進行這個工時調配
just don't let the same person
就是不要讓同一個人
Do a frequent exposure to high temperature thermal hazards
做一個常常曝曬到高溫熱危害
this is too serious
太嚴重的這個情況
So if his way of working hours is allocated
所以他這種工時調配的方式的話
reduce the heat hazard
就可以減低這個熱危害
OK
OK
over here
那這邊的話
Everyone has seen that there is a
大家有看到說這邊有一個
goats
羊散吧
are you happy
有沒有很高興
It's just that someone is finally going to break up these laborers
就是終於有人要替這些勞工打散了
No, I lied to you
不是啦 騙你們的
good self-deception
好 補自騙的
It's true that there were breakups at the construction site
是真的是在工地有打散
but not for labor
但是不是為了勞工
OK
OK
It's an underground archaeological site
那是一個地下考古長址
OK he was actually trying to prevent this
OK 他其實是為了防止這個
Archaeological artifacts scattered by sun-baked camps
考古文物受到日曬旅營所散的
In fact, the bottom line
那其實底下的話
Because of the dispersion, it is more stuffy
因為有散 反而更悶熱
OK so actually
OK 所以其實
In fact, this is both good and bad.
其實這個有好有壞了
Then when we actually do it on the spot
那我們實際現場做的時候
Except this worker has this wearable
除了是這個勞工有帶這個穿戴式裝置
We also have this on site with this mobile weather observer
我們在現場也有這個放置這個機動式的氣象觀測儀
Because some laborers
因為有些勞工因為工作的關係
It's inconvenient to have these devices on your body
它不方便身上有穿戴這些裝置
So let's also try
所以我們也試著一下
Look, if there is a mobile weather observer
看說如果是有一個機動式氣象觀測儀的話
Is it possible to explain them this too?
是不是也可以解釋他們這個
Measure roughly
大致上測量下
they may be exposed to heat hazards
他們可能遭受到熱危害
Let's also compare it with the battle of the Meteorological Bureau, which is one or two kilometers away.
我們也跟這個一兩公里之外的這個氣象局的戰去做比較
Here is our data
以下是我們的這個數據
Let's take a look, this is actually
大家來看一下這個其實是
A time sequence from nine o'clock in the morning until the afternoon when you get off work
一個時序屠從早上九點來直到下午這個下班的時候
ok
ok
What about these red lines are these five different workers
那這些紅色線呢都是這些五個不同的勞工
Five different workers each day
每天有五個不同的勞工
ok
ok
That blue, dark blue line is the mobile meteorological instrument we have on site
那藍色的 深藍色的線是我們在現場那個機動式的氣象的儀器
And the blue line is the weather station of the Meteorological Bureau that is farther away.
而且藍色的線的話就是比較遠一點的那個氣象局的氣象站
It's obvious here
那這邊可以很明顯
Apparently seeing the weather station, the temperature of labor timing may be five or six degrees worse
明顯看到氣象站 勞工時機的熱圍還可能會差個五六度
Even the blue people on the scene may sometimes be two or three degrees off
甚至現場藍色的人可能有時候都差個兩三度
It means that the promotion of workers is actually affected by many reflections, whether it is heat-absorbing steel bars, cement, wood boards or corrugated boards.
表示勞工其實晉升受到很多的 不管是吸熱的鋼筋 水泥 木板 或者是浪板反射的作用
Let me show you again. We know that the black flag is 32.2. There is a black flag drawn here.
再跟大家看一下 我們知道這黑旗是32.2 這邊有畫了一個黑旗
So most of the time here is actually in the afternoon because of the heavy thunderstorm, so everyone went on vacation
所以大部分的時間 這邊的話其實是下午因為下大雷雨 所以大家都放假去了
During thunderstorms, the construction industry cannot work for fear of danger, so there is no work for this matter.
雷雨的時候營造業是不能夠工作的 怕危險 所以這個事情是沒有工作的
But under other circumstances, you can see that most of their time, working time may be more than 65%
但是其他的情況之下 大家可以看到其實他們大部分的時間 工作的時間可能百分之六十五以上
All of them are under the status of WPGT is black flag, so it shows the situation of their industry
全部都是在WPGT是黑旗的狀態之下 所以顯示他們造業的情況
Gao Shou's siege of flesh is actually quite serious.
高受的這個 肉圍害的情況其實是蠻嚴重的
But we asked the worker
可是我們有問這個勞工
Workers don't really want a holiday
勞工其實並不想要放假
because they are everyday
因為他們是每天每天
Profitable
賺天的
He only makes a day's money for every day he works
他只每上工一天他就賺一天的錢
so he has no interest in vacation
所以他對於放假沒有興趣
what do they want
那他們要的是什麼
They want it to be like the Law Enforcement Office
他們是希望就像勞安所這樣子
That is, if someone moves it or arranges it during working hours
就是如果有人搬的或是工時調配的
or even they some employers are better
或甚至他們有些僱主比較好
That is, from 12:00 noon to 3:00 p.m., there is no need to do anything
就是中午12點到下午3點就說不用做事
He just rests but he gets off work late
他就是休息 但是他晚點下班
they would like to do it like this
他們願意是這樣子做
So they also reduce their own meat damage
所以他們也減少他們自己的肉圍害
Then it won't affect their money making
然後也不會影響到他們的賺錢
This is a win-win situation
這樣子的話才是雙贏的情況
everyone can see say
大家可以看到說
when we measure
我們在做測量的時候
In fact, it can also be clearly seen
其實也可以明顯看到
Sometimes they go to blow the air conditioner
他們到有時候有時候是去吹冷氣
during lunch break
中午休的時候
There will be this red line that is down and down
就會有這個紅線就是下降降下來
Said that they were lucky to have a real rest during their lunch break
表示他們還好午休的時候有真的休息到
This is the real situation in the labor workplace
這個是在勞工的作業場所真實的情況
So let's talk about this regression
所以我們這個回歸講就說
We explore the vulnerability of this thermal hazard
我們探討這熱危害的脆弱度
I just talked a lot about measuring WBGT
剛剛講了很多是測量WBGT的
If we look at it in July 2013
我們以2013年7月份來看的話
Probably the highest in Taipei
大概在台北是最高
Then we divide into 7 equal parts
然後我們分7等分
The red word means it is the most serious
這個紅色的話就表示是最嚴重的
The northern part is the same as the Taichung area
北部的跟這個台中地區
Possibly the highest WBGT
可能是WBGT最高
In terms of sensitivity
那就敏感度來講的話
In fact, the proportion of the elderly population is relatively high
其實是這個老年人口比例比較高
The population of young children is relatively high
幼外人口比較高的
like this Huadong area
像這個花東地區
so it's red
所以是紅色的
that they are the most sensitive
表示他們最比較敏感
Then we also consider the existing
那我們也考慮的是現有的
Cardiovascular disease visits
心臟血管疾病就診的情況
we also took it into consideration
我們也考慮進去了
to draw this sensitivity map
來畫這個敏感性的地圖
In terms of shadow ability
在陰影能力這個方面
We consider the community's
我們考量的是包括這個社區的
its this medical resource
它的這個醫療資源
The ratio of their air conditioner
他們這個冷暖氣機的比例
and his community
還有他這個社區
this society
這個有的這個社會
It should say community development association, etc.
應該說是社區發展協會等等
The number of these social organizations
這些社會組織的多寡
Then draw this map
然後來畫這個地圖
Everyone can take a look
大家可以看一下
In fact, the central region
其實中部地區
ok even
ok 甚至是
In the area of ​​Ganan
加南這個地區的話
Response ability is relatively weak
因應能力是比較弱一點的
so red is the worst
所以是紅色是最嚴重的
Okay, let's combine these three dimensions
好 我們把這三個面向綜合的話
You can draw the whole of Taiwan
就可以畫出全台灣的
This map of vulnerability to thermal hazards
熱危害的脆弱度的這個地圖
It can also be clearly seen here
這邊也可以明顯看出
Although the northern region
雖然北部地區
It seems that the risk is higher
好像受到的負險比較高
But because of the strong response ability
但是因為因應能力比較強
The characteristics of the population are also less sensitive
人口的特徵也沒有那麼敏感
So it's actually only a few
所以它其實只有少數
A place with a relatively high population
保年人口比較高的地方
belong to the sixth level of high vulnerability
是屬於這個第六級的高脆弱
Others are fine
其他的還好
central words
中部的話
Instead it is because
反而是因為
Central and Yoga South
中部跟瑜伽南這個部分
Possibly a relationship of lower coping capacity
可能是因應能力較低的關係
So the vulnerability is higher
所以使得脆弱度比較高
Next is the part of Pingtung
再來是屏東這個部分
Taitung Night Market
台東也是
Of course, this vulnerability will change with the change of society.
這個脆弱度當然會隨著社會的變遷
including population changes
包括人口的變遷
Changes in social conditions
社會條件的變遷
with us this
跟我們這個
Changes in the risk situation environment
負險情況環境的變遷而變
So this is actually a rolling
所以這個其實是一個滾動式
can be modified in the map
可以在修正的地圖
If our government has a good countermeasure
我們如果政府有很好的因應對策的話
We can also use this vulnerability map to see
我們也可以用這個脆弱度的地圖來看看
So his coping strategy
所以他的因應對策
Does it help various regions after implementation
執行之後是不是有幫助各個地區
to reduce their vulnerability
來減低他們的脆弱度
That's what vulnerability maps are for
這都是脆弱度地圖的目的
So what we just mentioned is
所以我們剛剛提到的就是
Vulnerability to this thermal hazard
這個熱危害的脆弱度
straight up climate change
直接講的是氣候變遷
How to impact our sensitive community
怎麼樣衝擊到我們的敏感的社群
its exposure, its response
它的曝顯、它的因應
However, in addition to the direct impact
可是其實除了直接的影響之外
There is also an indirect pathway of influence
還有一個間接的影響途徑
That is by affecting air pollution
那就是透過影響空氣污染
when the temperature is high
在溫度高的時候
The volatility of many pollutants is relatively high
很多污染物質的揮發性也比較高
Its photochemical work is also relatively strong
它光化作業也比較強
Therefore, there are more pollutants in production and survival
所以生產生存的污染物也多
and some are
還有一些就是
when the temperature is high
在這個溫度高的時候
sometimes it's this
有的時候它這個
The conditions for domineering diffusion are bad
霸氣的擴散條件反而不良
For example, there was this high pressure a few days ago
譬如說前幾天有這個高壓
hot high pressure
叫熱高壓
High pressure is equivalent to
高壓的話就等於是
There is a cover on it
上面有個蓋子蓋住
OK submerged layer
OK 溺溫層
So there is this submerged layer phenomenon
所以有這個溺溫層的現象
Therefore, air pollutants are not easy to diffuse out.
所以空氣污染物反而不容易擴散出去
Therefore, the concentration of air pollutants will increase
所以會造成空氣污染物的濃度增加
words to people
對人來講的話
That is when he is in hot weather at the same time
就是他同時在熱天的時候
subjected to heat stress
遭受到熱壓力
Also under pressure from air pollution
也同時遭受到空氣污染來的壓力
What about the two pressures?
那這兩個壓力呢
Affected organs are all heart or lungs
影響的器官通通都是心臟或者是肺臟
may be cardiopulmonary organs
可以都是心肺血管的器官
As far as humans are concerned, this is double
就對人來講是雙重的這個
This um affects double pressure
這個這個影響雙重的壓力
so we are doing
所以我們在做
thermal vulnerability
熱脆弱度
Apple also polluted the air at the same time.
蘋果的時候呢也同步做了空氣污染的這個蘋果
At the same time, the most important words for that are
那同時那個針對的最主要的話是
The pollutant PM2.5
PM2.5這個污染物質
this is us
這個是我們
just mentioned
剛剛有提到
Generally speaking, what kind of interdisciplinary approach do we use
大致上我們是用什麼樣的跨領域的方式
And then actually target other than doing this
然後其實針對除了做這個
In addition to the distribution of this heat hazard in geography
地理上面這個熱危害的分布之外
We actually also targeted air pollutants
我們其實也針對了空氣污染物
Our purpose is to hope to be able to construct
我們的目的的話都是希望能夠建構
Adaptation strategies based on scientific data
以科學資料為基礎的調適策略
That is how to do something better
也就是怎麼樣去做一些比較好的
Government policies can help us reduce
政府的政策能夠幫助我們降低
The impact and risk to health
對健康的這個衝擊跟風險
ok so this
好所以這個
The results of our first issue after we did
我們做了之後我們的第一期的結果
Thank you also to the Center for Sustainability for organizing a results presentation
也謝謝永續中心舉辦一個成果發表會
We invited representatives from 17 institutions
我們邀請了17個機關代表
covers a lot
涵蓋的非常多的
including the Department of Health and Welfare like the Bureau of Meteorology
包括像氣象局的衛福部
EPA, etc.
環保署等等
We are opening a lot of reps
我們在開了很多的代表
are very interested in our research results
都對我們的研究成果很有興趣
So there are words like this after the Meteorological Bureau and the Ministry of Health and Welfare
所以有像這個氣象局跟衛福部之後的話
They also asked us to continue the meeting
也有找我們再繼續去開會
see how we can help them
看我們怎麼樣能夠幫助他們
certain relevant policies
一定相關的政策
Like the Taipei City Environmental Protection Bureau and the Ministry of Labor
像這個臺北市環保局跟勞動部
Later also by the Bureau of Meteorology
後來也是由氣象局
They also suggested that these two units come to us
他們也是建議這兩個單位來找我們
to continue to do the next heat hazard effects
來繼續做接下來的熱危害的影響
So our policies
所以我們這些政策
In addition to saying to continue to communicate with these government units
除了說繼續跟這些政府單位溝通之外
other words
另外的話
I think it is very important to talk about how we can provide more miscellaneous stones
我想很重要就是說我們怎麼提供更雜石的
scientific data
科學的數據
can help them cope better
可以幫助他們一定更好的因應對策
That's what we're planning
這才是我們計畫中
this purpose
這個目的
then this part
那這個部分的話
And of course it also includes parts like air pollution
也當然也包括像空氣污染這個部分
ok
ok
Then this is what we do in the community
那這個是我們在社區裡面
We just talked about walking and jumping community
我們剛剛講走跳社區嘛
It's what we've done in the community
就是我們深入社區到底做了些什麼事
we are at ground level
我們在地面層
good or level
好或者是高度層
have placed these
有放置這些
device for sampling or observing
採樣或觀測的裝置
just mentioned
剛剛已經提到
with meteorological heat hazards
有氣象方面的熱危害的
Actually other words
其實其他的話
All are air pollutants
全部都是空氣污染物的
including solarizations like this
包括像這個太陽化物
Here are some precursors of pn2.5
這是pn2.5的一些前驅物質
Then pn2.5 still has ergodic distribution
那pn2.5還有歷經分布
And then there's black charcoal, which is toxic to health
然後還有是對健康有毒害性的黑炭
And how cold is the direction to listen to this or something like this
以及多寒方向聽這之類的這個
monitor
監測
That's just
那不過
then we still have
那我們還有
Use this green paper to collect samples for component analysis
用這個綠紙去採的樣來做成分分析
However, these component analyzes take a lot of time to do.
那不過這些成分分析都需要很多的時間來去做
this analysis
這個分析
So today's words are not
所以今天的話還不
You have a way to report this data to everyone
你有辦法跟大家報告這方面這個數據
ok so let's go first
好所以我們先
look again
再看一下
Our definition of overhang
我們這個懸覆的定義
Why do we care so much about this so-called pn2.5
我們為什麼那麼在意這個所謂pn2.5
ok
ok
this pn2.5
這個pn2.5
PM's words refer to suspension as force
PM的話是指的是懸浮為力
PM refers to the force of particle size less than 10 microns
PM時指的是歷勁小於10微米的為力
We don't care if it is greater than 10
大於10的我們就不在意了
why
為什麼呢
Because our nose hairs keep them out
因為我們的鼻毛會把他們擋在外面
So progress greater than 10 comes
所以大於10的進步來
unless
除非
unless you run
除非你跑步的時候
desperately open mouth to breathe
拚命張大口呼吸
At this time he may come in from your rouge
這個時候他可能會從你的胭口到進來
OK
OK
Otherwise it won't get into your nose
不然的話是進不到你的鼻子的
So we don't care if it is greater than 10
所以大於10的我們就比較不在意
from a health point of view
就健康的角度來看
That
那
Larger than 10 microns will come in
大於10微米的會進來
affects our upper respiratory tract
會影響到我們的上呼吸道
but only smaller than 2.5 microns
但是只有小於2.5微米的
can be implanted into our lung cannon
可以長驅植入到我們的肺炮
deep in the lungs
肺部的深處
Then it depends on what kind of pollutants he has
然後就看他到底有什麼樣的污染物質
what effect will it have on us
就會對我們造成什麼樣的影響
He is more able to penetrate our body
他是比較可以深入我們的身體
and accumulate over there
然後累積在那邊
long-term impact on us as a whole
對我們整體造成長期的影響
that some words are
那有一些的話是
This acute irritant
這個急性刺激作用
like acid flu
像流酸炎
That's something like listening in the cold direction
那有一些像多寒方向聽
He is spontaneous
他是有自來性的
And some if it's heavy metal
還有一些如果是重金屬的話
he is bad for nerves
他是對神經有獨壞的
So he sees what his ingredients are
所以他看他的成分是什麼
have different effects on our body
就會對我們身體有不同的影響
This is why I care so much about PN2.5
這是為什麼我那麼關心PN2.5
Source words of PN2.5
PN2.5的來源的話
It's not all man made.
其實也不是都是人造成的
some are of natural origin
有一些是自然源
So that's why the World Health Organization
所以這也是為什麼世界衛生組織
his annual
他訂的年度的
The recommended value for the annual average is 10 meters
年平均的建議值是10米
per cubic meter
每立方公尺
he didn't book zero
他沒有訂到零
because even if no one is there
因為就算人不在
In fact, nature still has
其實自然界還是會有
Man-made, of course, is factory emissions
人為的話當然就是工廠排放
Combustion activities Automobiles etc.
燃燒活動 汽機車等等
If distinguished by the process of the itinerary
以行程的過程來區分的話
He can also be divided into
他也可以分成是
Suspected pollutants discharged directly from the source
直接從來源排放的疑似汙染物
directly from the drain
就直接從排放口
Including factory emissions, automobile and motorcycle emissions
包括是工廠排放 汽機車排放
Kitchen fumes are directly discharged
廚房油煙直接排放
some air pollutants
也有一些是一些氣壯汙染物
When discharged, it is a gas
排放的時候是氣壯物
But he has undergone some photochemical reactions
可是他經過一些光化作用
after some action
一些作用之後
The prize of the itinerary
行程的利壯物
This is from the secondary
這個是由二次的
We call it secondary pollutant
我們叫它做二次污染物
after some process
經過一些過程
Pollutants emitted directly by
由直接排放的污染物
becomes an example
就變成了為例了
So PL2.5 is so difficult to control
所以PL2.5這麼難加以管控
It is because it has the process of secondary pollutants
就是因為它有二次污染物的過程
So even if we regulate pollutants once
所以即使我們管制了一次污染物
We still control many of its precursors
我們還是管制它很多的前驅物質
only valid
才有效
Otherwise it keeps generating this
否則它就會一直去生成這個
generate this secondary pollutant
生成這個二次污染物
this is our asia
這個是我們亞洲
But say this is global
但是說這個是全球的
2010 to 2012
2010年到2012年
Three-year global average of this PL2.5
三年的全球的這個PL2.5的平均
It can be seen that the Asian region is particularly red
可以看到亞洲地區特別紅
Just mentioned the World Health Organization
剛剛提到世界衛生組織的
The suggested value for the annual average is
年平均的建議值是
Ten Dimensional Meters
十維米美立方公尺
What about the Asian region?
那這個亞洲地區的話
It's possible to get to this 80 to 100
它的可以到這個80到100
What about the three-year average?
三年的平均呢
80 to 100 dimension meters
80到100維米
victor cubic meter
維克美立方公尺
OK very high
OK 非常的高
Of course it's also because of the Asian region
那當然也是因為亞洲地區
The economy has been booming in recent years
這些年來經濟發展很旺盛
this
這個
and it may be
而且它可能是
The control of the factory is not so strict
工廠的管制還沒有那麼嚴格所造成的
What about Taiwan?
那台灣呢
In the case of Taiwan, the Environmental Protection Agency has also made great efforts.
台灣的情況其實環保署也盡了非常大的努力
This air pollutant in Taiwan
台灣的這個氣壯污染物啦
For example, sulfur dioxide
譬如說是二氧化硫
it is also this
它也是這個
A precursor of PN2.5
PN2.5的一個前驅物
sulfur dioxide
二氧化硫啦
PN10 or PN2.5
PN10或者是PN2.5
In fact, there is a downward trend
其實都有下降的趨勢
So the EPA is not doing nothing
所以環保署並不是沒有做事
it does a lot of things
它做了很多的事情
Only then can such a decline be caused
才可以造成這樣子的這個下降
But what is everyone unhappy about now?
但是現在大家不高興的是什麼呢
not happy
不高興的是
because the World Health Organization says
因為世界衛生組織說
The annual average should be only ten meters
年平均應該是只有十為米
Ten is Kemei local factory
十為克美地方工廠
But we can't come down yet
可是我們目前還降不下來
ok our current words
ok 我們目前的話
Probably only the east is barely this
大概只有東部勉強這個
The average annual
年平均可以到
just under ten
就十以下
Otherwise, it is probably this
否則的話大概都是這個
3 40
3 40
It's even lower in recent years
甚至這幾年比較低了大概
about 2 30
大概2 30
ok
ok
That's because PN2.5 is considered a human carcinogen by the World Health Organization
那因為PN2.5是世界衛生組織認為的人類致癌物
so words
所以的話
That's why everyone cares so much
就是說大家才那麼在意
will hope to be able to lower and lower
才會希望能夠越降越低
Then let me mention it here
那我這邊跟大家提一下
Even after ambient concentrations drop
即使是環境濃度降下來之後
doesn't mean the front of your nose
也不表示你鼻子前面的
Exposure concentrations dropped below 10 microns
暴露濃度降到了10微米以下
OK
OK
Because of this exposure concentration
因為這個暴露濃度
It's the concentration in front of my nose
就是我鼻子前面的濃度
with the one they were testing
跟他們在測的這個
10 meters or more
10公尺以上
The EPA's measurements are usually above 10 meters
環保署的測量通常都在10公尺以上
It measures the uniform mixture of a city
它是測一個城市均勻混合的
concentration of air pollutants
空氣污染物的濃度
Its purpose is to compare
它的目的的話是比較
Is Taipei City better this year than last year?
台北市今年跟去年比有沒有比較好
Or compare it with Taipei City, Taichung, and Kaohsiung this year
或者是今年跟台北市跟台中跟高雄比
which city is better
哪個城市比較好
do it like this
是做這樣子的
so it's all evenly mixed
所以它都是均勻混合的
in front of our noses
跟我們鼻子前面
Probably especially this one in Asia
可能會尤其是亞洲的這個
In the community we just talked about
我們剛剛講的這個社區裡面
so many different sources of pollution
這麼多不同的污染源
OK
OK
including cars like this one
包括像這個汽機車的
discharge this temple directly
直接排放這個宮廟
Or a small factory in the catering industry, etc.
或者是餐飲業小工廠等等
If these are directly discharged
那這些直接排放的話
will cause us more
會造成我們更多的
the exposure concentration
這個曝露濃度
Exposure density
曝顯濃度
Let's take a look at how this pollutant will cause health and economic damage.
我們來看這個污染物怎麼樣會造成健康經濟損害這個歷程
Of course, our current industry or environmental protection policies will cause some pollution sources
當然是我們現在的產業或環保政策會造成有些污染源
Then what happens after these pollution sources are discharged?
然後這些污染源排放之後呢
After conversion, it will form the surrounding environment concentration just mentioned
經過轉換就會形成剛剛所提的周介環境濃度
Then this week, if the environmental concentration is going to affect our health
然後這周介環境濃度如果要能夠影響到我們的健康
we must be able to say
就一定要我們能夠就是說
This creates our external concentration
這個造成我們外在的瀑現濃度
we sucked in
我們吸進來了
The nose will inhale in order to affect our health
鼻子會吸進來才會影響到我們健康
Can't suck in
吸不進來的
won't come in
不會進來的
All will not affect our health
全部都不會影響到我們的健康
So the most important thing is actually the body's external concentration
所以最重要的其實是這個人體外在的瀑現濃度
The EPA is testing
那環保署在測呢
In fact, it is the surrounding concentration of pollutants
其實是污染物的周介濃度
It's actually like I just mentioned
它其實就像我剛剛提到了
It is not equal to the present concentration outside the human body
不等於這個人體外在的瀑現濃度
Extrinsic concentration of the human body
那人體外在的瀑現濃度
In fact, this is not easy to measure
其實這個並不好測量
I don't know if you have ever visited the EPA's test war
我不知道大家有沒有去參觀過環保署的測戰
About six or seven pollutants
大概六七種汙染物
It needs to fill a small room with a size of seven to ten pings
它要放滿七坪到十坪大的一個小房間
Different instruments and some cylinders
不同的儀器還有一些鋼瓶
OK
OK
so you can imagine
所以你可以想見
You have to measure the front of your nose
你要測你鼻子前面的
you can't take an instrument
你不可能拿一個儀器
Hold a cylinder and keep going
抱個鋼瓶一直走嘛
right
對不對
So to measure this dangerous concentration
所以要測這個破險濃度
It's not easy
其實並不容易
So it needs a portable observation instrument
所以它要用攜帶式的觀測儀器
to measure
來測量
Then this portable observation instrument
那這個攜帶式的觀測儀器
good enough
還要夠好夠準
for scientific purposes
才能夠去做科學的用途
OK
OK
So this is what we were doing before
所以這是我們之前在做這個
When this external dangerous concentration
這個外在破險濃度的時候
a big challenge
一個很大的一個挑戰
then one more word
那再一個的話
we should mention that
我們要提一下就是
In fact, the dangerous concentration of the human body
其實人體的這個破險濃度
because we are close
因為我們是近距離
including when we cook
包括像我們烹調的時候
including when we lose
包括像我們敗敗的時候
including before we ride a motorcycle
包括像我們在騎機車前
When a car emits black smoke
一個車這個排放黑煙的時候
what we inhaled
我們所吸到的呢
Actually a cutting-edge concentration
其實是一個尖端濃度
What about the tip concentration?
那個尖端濃度呢
EPA is undetectable
環保署是測不到的
Because it's gone in an instant
因為一瞬間就沒了
OK
OK
Therefore, the freshness measured by the concentration of Jannain
所以這個間奈濃度所測出來的這個新鮮
What about the concentration of the fresh pollutants it emits?
它排放的新鮮的這個汙染物質的這個濃度呢
or this ingredient
或者是這個成分
OK
OK
It is also different from the evenly mixed composition measured by the Environmental Protection Agency.
也跟環保署所測到的均勻混合之後的這個成分是不一樣的
OK because it's been hours
OK 因為它已經已經經過幾個小時了
OK
OK
So the composition is different and the concentration is not the same
所以這個成分不一樣濃度不一樣
so it actually
所以它事實上
If we use the concentration of the surrounding environment to represent the concentration we don't like
如果我們用周圍環境濃度來代表我們不嫌濃度的話
Many things behind are misleading
後面很多事情是會誤導的
including it would be misleading
包括它會誤導
our this
我們這個
how to measure us
怎麼樣去測量我們
The effect of actual damage to health
實際上的健康損害的效
Health Effect OK
健康效應 OK
health damage factor
健康損害係數
this is misleading
這是會誤導
that especially in
那尤其是在
With so many sources of pollution in this community in Taiwan
台灣這麼多的這個社區汙染源的情況之下
it may
它可能會
more misleading
誤導的更嚴重
Let's take a look at
我們看一下在
In fact, even in Europe and the United States
其實即使在歐美
Europe and the United States do not have such complex community pollution sources as ours
歐美還沒有我們這麼複雜的社區汙染源
Europe and the United States are relatively simple
歐美其實比較單純
Europe and the United States often say that
歐美常常講的是說
whatever it is
管它屬
Probably the concentration of PM2.5 in my backyard
大概就是我家後院的PM2.5的濃度
OK, if their family didn't mention some other sources of pollution
OK 那他們家如果沒有說其他一些污染源
Like this fast frying and so on
像這個大火快炒等等的話
probably that's about it
大概就是差不多是這樣
but even so
可是即使如此
let's take a look
我們看一下
If the ambient concentration is used to represent the acceptable concentration
如果是以周介環境濃度來代表不嫌濃度的話
We underestimate the health damage of pollutants
我們會低估污染物對健康的損害
This is a well-known one or two studies in the United States
這個是美國很有名的一個兩個研究
This is American Cancer Research
這個是美國癌症研究
there is a famous author
有一個很有名的作者
He is using urban monitoring stations to represent the concentration of people in the whole city
他是用城市監測站來代表全城的民眾的不嫌濃度
The result he got was
他得到的結果是
10 wick per rise
每上升10維克
PM2.5 per cubic meter
每立方公尺的PM2.5
His overall death rate will increase by 6%
他的總死亡率會上升6%
OK up 6%
OK 上升6%
that same one
那同一個
population in the same cancer cohort
同一個癌症世代的人口
this study
這個study
But different researchers
但是不同的研究者
He used a nearby monitoring station
他用附近的監測站
and he took into account different traffic flows
並且他考量了不同的交通流量
That is, different areas have different traffic flows.
就是不同區域有不同交通流量
Use such a more detailed method to estimate the population of the people
用這樣子比較細緻的方法來推估人口的人民的
exposure concentration
曝險濃度的話
what did he get
他得到的結果呢
Every rise of 10 victoria meters
每上升10個維克美地方公尺
The overall death rate will increase by 17%
總死亡率會上升17%
That is 3 times higher
也就是高出3倍
This is 3 times higher
這個高出3倍呢
It is because his exposure concentration estimation is more accurate
是因為他的曝險濃度的估計比較精準
What about this estimate?
這個估計呢
Also with the other one in Europe is also using
也跟歐洲另外一個也是利用
It is also a more accurate way of land return
他也是比較精準的土地回歸的方式
To estimate the concentration of exposure
來推估曝險濃度呢
The estimated 13% is relatively close
推估出來的13%是比較接近的
OK
OK
So scientifically speaking
所以在科學上來講
How can we get more accurate
我們怎麼樣去得到比較精確的
Exposure concentration is a very, very important issue
曝險濃度非常非常重要的一個問題
Because science is basically about finding the truth.
因為科學基本上就是在求真嘛
We have the closest true exposure concentration value
我們有最接近真實的曝險濃度值
We can compare to estimate
我們就比較可以推估到
More accurate this P2.5
比較精確的這個P2.5
How does it harm your health?
到底對於健康有怎麼樣的損害
At present, these large-scale studies in Europe and the United States
目前這些歐美的大的大型研究
Basically they're talking about long-term exposure to pollutants
基本上他們探討的都是污染物的長期曝露
long-term bleeding
長期的瀕血
Damage factor for long-term chronic health damage to health
對於健康的長期慢性的健康損害的損害係數
for acute injuries
對於急性的傷害
including what we just mentioned
包括我們剛剛提說
Emissions from cars and locomotives in front
前面的汽機車這樣的排放
or when we cook
或者是我們烹調的時候
Exposure to higher concentrations
比較高濃度的曝露
Such an exposure when I like barbecue on Mid-Autumn Festival
自己中秋節喜歡烤肉的時候的這樣一個曝露
What is the harm to our own health?
對於我們自己健康傷害是怎麼樣
Now, very little is known
現在的話其實很少知道
because of technical limitations
因為是技術上的限制
Fortunately, it is also because in recent years
還好也是因為近年來
Especially the technical limitations in the past two years
尤其是這兩年來技術上的限制
Our future is likely to be in this area
我們未來很可能在這方面
in the assessment of acute health effects
在急性的健康效應的評估這方面
can make better progress
可以有比較好的進步
This is also the direction our research team wants to work on in the future
這也是我們研究團隊未來想要努力的方向
ok let's see
好 我們看一下
We have been talking about the prevention and treatment of kidney stasis
我們一直在講說預防腎瘀治療
So in the middle of something like this
所以在這個樣子的環節中間
What in this process
這個歷程中到底哪些
is the point of entry where we can intervene policy
是我們可以政策介入的介入點
If we have better industrial and environmental protection policies
如果我們有比較好的產業跟環保的政策
In terms of environmental governance
以環境治理來講
We will reduce a lot of pollution sources
我們就少掉很多的污染源
that's the best, right?
那是最好的對不對
Prevention of Kidney Stasis Treatment
預防腎瘀治療
Or you discharge pollutants
或者是你污染物排放了
But I figured out how to prevent pollution from it
可是我想辦法從中污染防治
catch you
把你抓下來
OK this is OK
OK這也是OK
But there is no 100% pollution in the world
可是世界上沒有100%的污染的
100% pollution control equipment that can be caught
100%可以抓下來的污染防治設備
once it's discharged
一旦它排放了之後
The next one that can protect our health
下一個能夠保障我們健康的
That is, how do we think of ways to block this exposure channel?
就是我們想辦法怎麼樣去阻斷這個曝險途徑
so even in the air
所以即使在空氣中
But we won't be exposed to this
可是我們不會被這個曝險到
then we'll be safe
那我們就安全了
ok this is next
OK這是下一個
So these three points
所以這三個點
Basically, policy can intervene
基本上都是政策可以介入來
Points to reduce health risks
降低健康風險的點
Then our scientific problem is actually
那我們的科學問題其實就是
We want to know what the actual risk concentration of the people is
我們想要了解一下民眾到底實際的鋪險濃度是什麼
What kind of impact factor does that have?
那有什麼樣的影響因子
Are there potential sources of neglected pollutants?
是不是有一些被忽略掉的污染物的鋪險來源
we forget we ignore
我們忘記了 我們忽視了
Then there is how we can block this dangerous path
那還有就是我們怎麼樣去阻斷這個鋪險途徑
So can protect our health
所以可以保護我們的健康
This is what we did in Taiwan
這個是我們在台灣做的
This is a 400-meter community
這是一個400公尺的社區
Then we take the instrument
然後我們就帶著儀器
Walk along this street for about an hour and a half
沿著這個街道上就走了一圈大概一個半小時以內
You can see that its concentration is three times different
可以看到一下它的濃度的話差三倍
Concentrations can be three times higher in some places with polluting source community sources
在一些有污染排放源社區排放源的地方的話濃度會高三倍
This is what we call community pollution
這就是我們所提到的社區污染
The impact of community emission sources on the concentration of human hazards
社區排放源會對於我們人鋪險濃度的影響
It will also have an impact on the air quality of our communities
也是會對於我們社區的空氣品質的影響
So in Asia
所以在亞洲地區的話
In fact, Europe and the United States are really different
其實歐美真的不一樣
We are not only subject to
我們其實不只是受到
Influence of surrounding environment concentration
周介環境濃度的影響
OK Our Personal Concentration
OK 我們的個人的瀑顯濃度
environment
是收周介環境
Coupled with these increases in community emission sources
再加上社區排放源的這些增量
coupled with our individual behavior
再加上我們個人行為所產生的
including if you are going to smoke
包括如果你要抽菸的話
OK or cooking or doing any activity
OK 或者是烹調或者是做任何的活動
This is generated by pumping this self
這個是抽這個自己產生的
So what is the concentration of each of us?
所以我們每個人的瀑顯濃度呢
In fact, it is a combination of these three
其實是這三項的綜合
OK put together
OK 綜合在一起
so which one is more
所以到底是哪項多多少
that is, not everyone
就是每個人不一定
what about our team
那我們這個團隊呢
It's not always a survey
並不是每次都是在做調查
as if we researched this
好像我們研究了這個
How high are you this time, how low will you be next time
你這次多高 下次多低
it's over
就結束了
not like this
並不是這樣子
we're talking about forever
我們在探討永遠是
What is the factor
到底是什麼因子
will affect the concentration of the waterfall
會影響到這個瀑顯濃度
Then what is the emission of this waterfall?
那它這個瀑顯原的排放的量是多少
What is the increase in emissions
排放增量是多少
What is the emission factor
排放因子是多少
After having these
有了這些之後
In order to draw all these data together
才能把這些資料都繪整在一起
Then on the one hand, it is possible to estimate more precisely
然後一方面可以更精確的去推估
Our Risk Concentration
我們的瀑險濃度
So we can calculate
所以我們才可以去推算
to study our health damage coefficient
才去研究我們的健康損害係數
it's a purpose
這是一個目的
one more word
再一個的話
More importantly, we can also put
更重要的是我們也可以把
this factor of this risk
這個瀑險的這個因子
add up to one of us
累積起來放到我們一個
what we call catastrophe mode
我們所謂的瀑險模式
OK
OK
So in the future, this waterfall mode
所以將來的話這個瀑險模式
we can use
我們就可以用來
Do a lot of other science above this discussion
做很多其他的科學上面的這個探討
ok let's see
好 我們看一下
We are curious in this land
我們在這個大地很好奇
Are we usually in the community?
我們到底是平常在社區裡面
how to go around
怎麼樣在一面繞行的
OK
OK
Let me show you here
這邊給大家看一下
This is what we worked hard for
這個就是我們辛苦的
The assistant and the student
這個助理跟學生
It's really just a push cart
真的就是推了一個小推車
He has a very precise instrument on it.
他上面都是非常精密的這個儀器
OK detour along the community
OK 沿著社區繞行
and he can't go too fast
而且他也不能走太快
OK he has to walk slowly
OK 他要慢慢的走
So in very hot conditions
所以在很熱的情況之下
if you see this girl
你看到這個女生的話
Still wearing this visor hat
還戴著這個遮陽的帽
If this girl is on the side of the road
那這個女生在路邊的話
We also need to register some, including cars and motorcycles passing by the roadside
還要登記一些 包括像路邊經過的汽機車
He has to count, he has to do a lot of record work
他要數數目 他要做很多的記錄的工作
Only by recording it like this can we know
那這樣記錄下來我們才能知道說
Which factors will emit how much pollution increase
哪一些因子到底會排放多少的污染增量
Some passers-by will also be curious
有一些路人經過的話也會很好奇
so what are we doing
所以我們到底在幹嘛
And then we'll all tell him we're measuring the air quality
然後我們都會跟他講說我們在測空氣品質
Then he said good very good
然後他就說 好很好
We really need you to test this air quality
我們很需要你來測這個空氣品質
like this this car goes by
像這樣子這個汽車經過
This is actually when ordinary people are waiting for the red jade lantern.
這個其實都是一般人在等紅玉燈的時候
will stay at this intersection
會待著這個大馬路口
OK this is all in the alley
OK 這個都是在小巷子裡
we are simulating words
我們在模擬的話
In fact, we also saw old people who were about our height
其實我們也看到跟我們差不多高的老人家
He rides this car, do you have electric cars?
他騎著這個小車車 有沒有電動車
when he is walking or the baby is in the stroller
他在走或者是嬰兒在推車的時候
are also so high
也都是這樣高
So we are also simulating the actual
所以我們也都是在模擬這個實際上
when people actually do these everyday things
人們他們實際上在做這些日常生活的時候
The exposure concentration of
的這個暴露濃度
Then we also explore the factor behind him
然後我們也探討他背後的這個因子
This is a video of our live
這是我們實況的錄影
In fact, our personal PM2.5 concentration
其實我們個人PM2.5的鋪險濃度
technology over the years
這些年來在技術上面
Great progress has been made in the analysis of this observation technique
在分析這個觀測技術上面有很大的進步
We're going to have a pump before new year's
早新年的話我們要有一個幫浦
Connect a sampling head to pump air
接一個採樣頭要抽氣
So we're going to pump air with a filter paper in it
所以我們要抽氣裡面有個濾紙
So you can accumulate PM2.5
所以可以累積PM2.5
Its advantage is that this filter paper can also be used for chemical analysis later
它的好處是這個濾紙之後還可以去做化學分析
will analyze some ingredients that are harmful to health
就會分析些對健康有害的成分
its downside is
它的壞處是
I actually took this myself
其實我自己有帶過這個
This set is about 2.5 kg
這個一套的話大概是2.5公斤
You will think that this 2.5 kg is nothing
你會覺得這個2.5公斤不算什麼
right
對
It also vibrates a little bit
它還有稍微一點點的振動
You'll feel like the first five minutes are nothing
你會覺得剛開始五分鐘不算什麼
You'll know after you vibrate it for half an hour
你振它半小時之後你就知道了
It vibrated to the point where I couldn't do anything else that day
它振到我那天完全沒有辦法做其他的事情
i can only watch tv
我只能看電視
you can't think
你沒有辦法思考
Because it just doesn't work and keeps vibrating inside
因為它就是一直不行在裡面一直振動
and it's going to be a little bit noisy
而且它還會有點些微的噪音
that noise too
那個噪音也是
The first five minutes you thought it was okay
前五分鐘你覺得是無所謂
then wait until half an hour
然後等到半小時
Then I started to feel unbearable
之後就覺得開始受不了了
So we're also grateful for the years
所以我們也很感謝這些年來
The assistants and volunteers who helped us bring these observation instruments
幫我們帶這些觀測儀器的助理跟志願者
Then they have to take 4 hours to 24 hours
那他們要帶4個小時到24小時
OK take so long before we can collect enough
OK 帶這麼久我們才能夠收集到足夠的量
to do chemical analysis
才能夠去做化學分析
OK this was 20 years ago
OK 這是20年前
Then I came to Academia Sinica
那後來我來中研院了
So I am very grateful that Academia Sinica has money to support
所以很感謝中研院有錢去支持
We bought a western belt for this
這個我們就買了一個西帶式的
The particle regime instrument
這個微粒製度儀器
It is possible to measure this particle size distribution
它是可以測量這個粒徑分布
Also includes PN2.5
也包括PN2.5
This is about two to three kilograms
這個的話大概也差不多是兩三公斤左右
OK but because it's too expensive
OK 但是因為它太貴重了
So we can only sell these two sets
所以我們也只能賣這個兩套
And it was brought by my assistant
而且是由我的助理來帶
We dare not bring volunteers
我們也不敢給志願者帶
Because if it hits
因為它萬一撞的話
We're about to pass out
那個我們就快昏倒了
OK, then we can collect one piece of data per minute
OK 那我們可以收集到一分鐘一筆數據
Now, we are cooperating with the teachers of the information center
那現在的話我們是跟資訊所的老師合作
So now it has developed like this
所以現在已經發展出這樣子簡直
Simple, this one is only 200 grams
簡單的,這一個才200克
it is paired with a
它就是配上一個
mobile power bank
手機的行動電源
Then it can also be equipped with temperature and humidity inside
然後它還可以配上,裡面還有溫度濕度
Then this GPS and Wi-Fi, it can transmit wirelessly
然後這個GPS跟Wi-Fi,它可以無線傳輸
There is also an SD card, which can save its data
還有SD card,就是可以把它資料存起來
There can be a data every 15 seconds
每15秒就可以有一筆數據
So if the instrument of research like now
所以像現在這樣的研究的儀器的話
We can study more later
我們以後可以研究更多
The client's liability, and the acute liability
這個客人的負險,還有就是急性的負險
relationship with health effects
跟健康效應之間的關係
This is what we designed this year
這個是今年我們才設計出來的
we started early
我們從很早開始
we were in 1999
我們就在1999年
We are actually in six communities in the north, central and south
我們事實上就在北中南六個社區
to recruit volunteers
去招募志願者
Thank you to the five or sixty volunteers
謝謝當初五、六十個志願者
Willing to wear a sampler like this
願意配戴這樣子的採樣器
Wear it 24 hours a day
配戴24小時,就一整天
when they wear
他們在配戴的時候
They also help us fill out questionnaires
他們還要幫我們填問卷
He just told us every 30 minutes
他就是每30分鐘他告訴我們說
Was he indoors or outdoors at that time?
他那個時候在室內還是室外
Is there any source of pollution near him?
他附近有沒有什麼污染源
including someone smoking
包括有人抽菸啦
There is this car exhaust
有這個汽機車排氣啦
There is this family setting off firecrackers
有這個人家放鞭炮啦
what are these details
有什麼的這些細節
then what is he doing
然後他在做什麼事
he is riding a motorcycle
他是在騎機車呢
still here
還是在這個這個
do any of this activity
做任何的這個活動
ok watching tv and so on
ok在看電視等等的
That's because we need this schedule of his activities
那因為我們需要他的這個活動時間表
to be able to analyze
才能夠去分析
Why on earth do some people have high concentration
到底為什麼有些人濃度高
Some people have lower concentrations
有些人濃度比較低
Because we can only accumulate one data in 24 hours
因為我們24小時只能累積一筆數據
ok at that time
ok那個時候
What about this research?
那當年的這個研究呢
actually very very important
其實是非常非常重要
This is the first in Taiwan
這個是第一個在臺灣地區
This is actually in the community
這個在實際上在社區裡面
See this study on particulate exposure
看微粒暴露的這個研究
Then he is targeting PM10
那他是針對PM10
At that time, there was no PM2.5
那時候還沒有針對PM2.5
What about this study?
那這個研究呢
In fact, this electric
其實這個電電的
The basis of my future research
我以後很多研究的基礎
he pointed out two
他指出兩個
In fact, in European and American studies
其實在歐美研究上
rarely pointed out
很少指出來的事情
First
第一個
Research tells us that indoor air quality
研究都告訴我們說室內的空氣品質
Concentrations of pollutants are higher indoors than outdoors
室內的污染物濃度都會比室外高
Because Europe and the United States don’t care if they have cats and dogs at home
因為歐美不管他們家裡是因為有養貓狗
Because of the carpet or something
因為有地毯或是有什麼樣的情況
Although they are not decorated with high heat, quick fry or burn incense
雖然他們沒有裝飾大火快炒或者是燒香
But their indoor concentration is really relatively high
可是他們的室內濃度真的就是比較高
Indoor is higher than outdoor
室內比室外高
we are the opposite
我們是相反的
We are higher outdoor than indoor
我們是室外比室內高
At first, I felt a little bit unconvinced.
剛開始我還覺得有點不太相信
I later discussed with other researchers in public health
後來我又跟公衛界的其他的研究者討論
They said that the few cases they tested were actually like this
他們說他們測出來少數的例子其實也是這樣子
what does that mean
這表示什麼呢
This means that we are actually too dirty outside.
這表示其實我們是室外太髒了
OK
OK
real
真的
OK because we really have a lot of community pollution sources outdoors
OK 因為我們室外真的有不少的社區污染源
This is why it continued to be a source of community pollution.
這是為什麼後來就持續的做了社區污染源
Because it is from the outdoors of the community
因為就是從社區的戶外
it passes
它就傳
because you don't care how it closes the window
因為你不管它怎麼關窗
it just has air exchange
它就是會有空氣交換
it comes from outside to inside
它從室外傳到室內來
OK will affect the indoor air quality
OK 會影響到室內的空氣品質
very different
很不一樣的
Second point
第二點
Actually doing this abroad
其實在國外做這個
powerless personal exposure
為力的個人曝露
personal exposure
個人曝顯
maybe make it out
可能做出來就是說
main conclusion
最主要的結論
It may be that people who smoke have a higher concentration
可能就是抽菸的人濃度比較高
probably their most important one
大概他們最重要的一個
The exposure factor is this
曝顯的因子是這個
but we make it
可是我們做出來
Like the 50 or so people I recruited
像我招募的這個50幾個人
Actually they don't smoke
其實都是不是抽菸的
the non-smoker
這個非吸菸者
But they have different
可是他們有各種不同的
This exposed behavior
這個曝顯的行為
will make their concentration
會讓他們的濃度
Individual concentration is higher than others
個人的濃度是比別人高
the most obvious
那幾個最明顯的
What about this exposed behavior?
這個曝顯的行為呢
the first motorcycle
第一個騎機車
biker outside
在外面騎機車的人
He's just taller than a guy who doesn't ride a bike
他就是比沒有騎機車的人要高
he average
他平均來講
his concentration words
他的濃度的話
High exposure concentration of 20 gram
曝顯濃度高20維克
per cubic meter
每立方公尺
In addition, people who are slightly defeated are also
再加稍相敗敗的人也是
and the ones in the kitchen
然後待在廚房的也是
stay in the kitchen
待在廚房喔
not my own cooking
不是自己這個烹調
Because we all asked him about this activity
因為我們都有問他的這個活動嘛
it's him in the kitchen
就是他待在廚房
with his wife or his mother
陪他的太太或是他的媽媽
this chat
這個聊天的
His negative risk concentration will be high
他的負險濃度都會高
And these households actually have range hoods for driving
而這些家戶其實都有開車油煙機
ok, but his negative risk concentration will still be relatively high
ok 可是他的負險濃度還是會比較高
there is another
另外還有一個
It is time to pass the small community factory
是經過社區小工廠的時候
ok because we have too many Taiwan
ok 因為我們台灣太多
weird little factory
奇奇怪怪的小工廠
Our so-called small factories are actually a lot of traffickers
我們所謂的小工廠其實是販子很多
Like this motorcycle repair shop, small carpenter, etc.
像這個機車修理店啊小木工啊等等
The shop and business of metal, etc. are all
金屬的這個店和業等等都是
ok after these
ok 經過這些的
he didn't go in he just passed by
他沒有進去 他只是經過
he will be taller
他就會比較高
ok, so these, these, and this information
ok 所以這些這些這個資料的話
that's why we will
就是為什麼我們以後會
Research this community pollution source
研究這個社區污染源
ok now a quick word on this
好 現在很快的講一下這個
Everyone in Asia knows this
亞洲這些大家都很清楚
we are all around
我們就是生活周遭
we because we like to have
我們因為我們喜歡有
good life function
很好的生活機能
Our family can eat a lot of this car
我們家能口很多的這個汽機車
Gongmiao, this hair salon
宮廟啊這個美髮店
wait for the night market
等等的 夜市
ok
ok
Then these words will emit these pn2.5
那這些的話都會排放這些pn2.5
some are direct emissions
有些是直接排放
It also does not require secondary pollution
它還不用二次污染
It emits a lot of direct emissions
它是直接排放就排放很多
Then this is our community
那這個是我們在社區
Actually use the more expensive one
實際上用那個比較貴的這個
instrument to do
儀器來做
Gongmiao next to the catering industry
在餐飲業旁邊公廟
beside
旁邊
Most people wait for the work toilet to see
一般人等工廁的地方去看
After all, these will cause
說到底會 這些會造成
How much concentration increments do we
我們多少的濃度的增量
then we also
然後我們也
This is one of the materials
這個是一個 其中的一個資料
this is to see this
這個是看這個
This filter distributes
這個濾鏡分佈
That's 0.1 microns and all the way up to 100
這是0.1微米 然後一直到100
so we can see
所以我們可以看到
The words behind are background points
後面的話是背景點
very light color
很淡的顏色
The word before that is the catering industry
那前面的話是餐飲業
So we can know the words of the restaurant industry
所以我們可以知道餐飲業的話
it is
它是
Possibly larger filters
可能排放比較大的濾鏡
or emit into very, very small filters
或者是排放到非常非常小的濾鏡
The words of Gongmiao
那工廟的話
Almost the emissions are exactly what we breathe
幾乎就是排放剛好是我們呼吸
It is like this below pn2.5
就是pn2.5以下的這樣
this range
這個範圍
The emission from the factory site is relatively large.
那工廠工地排放的是比較大的
filter range
濾鏡範圍
From these we can see that comparing
我們由這些就可以看出比較一下
Emission sources in this different community
這個不同的社區的排放源
The vili that was released was actually
排出來的這個維力其實
Different circumstances
歷境分不適有差異的
In addition, we can also use this statistical method
另外的話我們也可以用這個統計的方法
How to analyze data
資料分析的方法去看說
These catering industry with oily fumes
這些有油煙的餐飲業
Temple construction site etc.
宮廟建築工地等等
All for our PN2.5
都對於我們這個PN2.5
Wait, there is this obvious contribution
等等有這個明顯的這個貢獻量
Then everyone probably in the past five years or
那大家大概在過去五年或者是
Only noticed in the past week or two
過去一兩禮拜才會注意到
This temple minus this thing
這個寺廟減鄉的這個事情
In fact, because I made this incense-related
其實因為我做這個燒香相關的
This study has been done for more than ten years
這個研究做了十多年
So I actually spent the past few years in this
所以我其實在這個過去這些年
do these studies
做這些研究呢
I was also invited to this
我也受邀到這個
Like last year, there were two chances to go to Central
像去年有兩次的機會到中部
This is the local religious group
這個是當地的宗教團體
They are spontaneous to promote
他們是自發性的去推廣
Events at Eco-friendly Temples
環保寺廟的活動
Really try to use self-management as much as possible
真的是盡量用自主管理的方式
Minimize
盡量減量
So we've actually seen over the years
所以我們在這些年是確實看到
They're really pushing the same box
他們真的就是在推行一如一箱
When I used to do
以前的話我做的時候
In fact, some are like three incense sticks or more
其實是有些是一如三支香或是更多
OK
OK
So they really have this
所以他們真的已經這個
tried my best
盡了很大的努力了
Of course the EPA is also kind
那當然環保署也是好意
Because it is true that when you burn incense and fail
因為確實你燒香敗敗的時候
you hold it in front of your nose
你是拿在鼻子前面
So you are this about your health
所以你對你的健康是這個
Your invisibility is very high
你的不顯量是很高的
OK is bad for your health
OK 是對健康不好的
so good intentions on both sides
所以兩邊都是好意
But in the end this
可是到最後這個
There may be some misunderstandings in the middle
中間可能有一些誤會
OK
OK
Well, I've been talking to this environmental group over the years
好 我這些年來跟這個環保團體
or a religious group
或者是宗教團體
when this interaction
這個互動的時候
Learned a lot from them
也跟他們學到很多
the first they also say
第一個他們也講說
This proverb says
這個俗語講
Burning incense from fortune telling
從算命付燒香
OK, why is it that the one who pays burns incense?
OK 為什麼是付的人才燒香呢
Because the incense used to be very expensive
因為以前的香很貴
They are all made with very precious traditional Chinese medicine.
都是用非常珍貴的中藥才做的
So it burns out very
所以它燒出來是很
This is very fragrant and comfortable
這個很香很舒服的味道
Not now, now there are a lot of annual plans to study medicine
現在不是,現在是一大堆的年作計畫學藥
In fact, if it burns out, it is very likely that there will be a lot of sperm and eggs
其實它燒出來的話,很可能一大堆的有精卵物
I myself have done research on the direction of cancer treatment, and analyzed it
我自己都去做治癌方向經的研究,分析出來
Then other scholars have also made it, and you have burned heavy metals
那其他的學者也有做出,你們有燒出重金屬的
This is all published in the literature
這個都是文獻上是有發表的
So the fragrance of the past is different from the fragrance of the present
所以以前的香跟現在的香不一樣
In addition, the refinement of the past is not the same as the refinement of the present.
另外以前的精緻也跟現在的精緻不一樣
The one in the middle of the previous exquisiteness is Xibo
以前的精緻中間那一塊是錫波
Now the middle is plastic, what will the plastic burn out
現在的話中間是塑膠,塑膠會燒出什麼
We all know, waist type
大家知道吧,帶腰型
So this is where there are many differences between the past and the present
所以這個就是以前跟現在有很多不一樣的地方
But these religious groups are actually trying to do
但是這些宗教團體事實上它也在努力在做
These are the words of the local faith center
這些的話都是當地的信仰中心
We also selected these two recent reports
這個我們也選了這兩個最近的報導
In fact, it also shows that these religious groups
其實也顯示說這些宗教的團體
They are actually very considerate of everyone.
他們其實是非常為大家著想的
For example, when passing the examinee's place, he is forbidden to become
譬如說經過考生的地方,他就是禁止變成
Bubble and loudspeaker while playing
邊放邊泡跟擴音器
let the grill suffer
讓烤身受到影響
Or when Mazu is oily
或者是媽祖出油的時候
Also do not let the side soak along the way
也是沿途不放邊泡的
They are also promoting environmental protection
他們也都是在推廣環保
concept of health
跟健康的觀念
I have been from 1999 to now
我從1999年到至今
I did a series of
我做了一連串的
There are experiments related to burning incense
有跟燒香有關的實驗
including watching in the lab
包括在實驗室裡看
different edema
不同的香腫
It's burned out PN2.5
它的燒出來的PN2.5
Shout out to the Fragrance Hall
跟獨喊放香廳
Then we are in this
然後我們在這個
Xiangke at home
相客在家裡
defeat every day or
每天敗敗或者是
go to temple every month
每月去寺廟敗
or this
或者是這個
When talking about Mazu looking in the mirror
大講馬祖照鏡的時候
what are they
他們到底是
how much exposure
暴露到多少
What else is this impact factor
還有哪些這是影響因子
OK
OK
then i emphasize
那我著重的話
have always been
都一直是
controllable factors
可控制的因子
what factor
就是什麼因子
can help him reduce his risk concentration
可以幫助他降低他的鋪險濃度
I've been telling this student
我都一直在跟這個學生說
or when people communicate
或者是民眾溝通的時候
speaking
在講說
our purpose
我們的做的目的
I hope to say how to go
是希望說怎麼樣去
keep the tradition
保有傳統的
Folk while reducing health risks
民俗 同時降低對健康的風險
In fact, that's what I told the gods
其實我也是這樣對神明講的
when i go to the temple to do it
我去寺廟去做的時候
I must first worship the gods
我一定都先拜神明
And speak to him very reverently
而且很虔誠地跟他講說
I'm not trying to change folklore beliefs
我不是要改變大家的民俗信仰
I hope everyone engages in the same folk beliefs when
我希望大家從事同樣的民俗信仰的時候
How to reduce the risk to your health
怎麼樣去降低對自己的健康的風險
So most of the gods agree that I am in the temple
所以大部分的神明都同意我在寺廟
Do observations like this
做這樣子的觀測活動
only one did not agree
只有一家沒有同意
I asked three times and he still didn't agree
我問了三次他還不同意
I just thank him
我就謝謝他
I'm leaving
我就走了
that's all
就這樣子而已
so we just respect
所以我們就是很尊重
events like temples
寺廟這樣的活動
So like I would suggest
所以像我的話就會建議
When everyone is burning incense
大家在燒香的時候
The first must be ventilated
第一個一定要通風
of course we all know
當然我們都知道說
Telescope with censer
與香爐的遠鏡
will also affect the concentration of the waterfall
也會影響到瀑顯的濃度
But ventilation is the most important
但是通風最重要
It doesn't matter if you're close to him as long as it's ventilated
只要通風你離他近一點都沒有關係
The concentration of ventilation can be as bad as
通風的濃度的話可以差到
seven or eight times more
七八倍以上
Xiangzhi tree, Xianglulu, etc. used in temples
在寺廟中所使用的香芝樹香蘆蘆等等的
Or when Dajia Matsu circled in
或者是在大甲馬祖繞進的時候
For everyone, it is better to take this kind of big bus.
為請大家就是坐著這種大巴士去比較好
Otherwise, you will directly ride a motorcycle and be directly exposed to more serious
不然的話你會直接騎機車還會直接被曝露到更嚴重
These are controllable factors
這些都是可控制的因子
In addition, we also want to talk about this walking and jumping night market
另外的話我們也想講一下這個走跳夜市
This is actually my favorite night market.
這其實是我很喜歡去的這個夜市
This night market is not the night market on the promotional materials
這個夜市不是宣傳品上的夜市
it's different
這不一樣
Another word is because our data is made with sensors
再一個的話因為我們這個資料是用感測器做出來的
So it hasn't been corrected by this science
所以還沒有經過這個科學的校正
It's just that there is a trend now that I can show it to everyone
只是說現在有這個趨勢可以秀給大家看
If we're here, we're entering a palace
我們在這邊的話是進到一個宮廟內
Its concentration will increase a lot
它的濃度就會上升很多
then we passed a lot of kebab places
然後我們經過很多烤肉店
Yakiniku stand, chicken cutlet
烤肉攤、炸雞排
or charcoal grilled milk
或是炭火乳烤
This rise is most pronounced
這個上升的情況最明顯
OK
OK
There are three leading military systems here
這邊的地方有三位引軍制
I'm actually about five meters away from them.
其實我已經離他們大概五公尺了
In fact, it will also affect
事實上都還會影響到
we know how serious
我們就知道有多嚴重
And these like passing through the incense burner or the convenience store
還有這些像經過香爐或者是便利商店
Wait in the underground parking lot
地下停車場裡面等等
There are also such
也都有這樣子的
There is this obvious pick out
有這個很明顯的pick出來
So in the future we will have a smaller one like this
所以以後我們有這樣子比較微型的
some sensor words
一些感測器的話
can help us do more
就可以幫助我們做更多
this
這個
Then this actually helps
然後這個其實也可以幫助
Ordinary people to understand his daily life
一般的民眾去了解他日常生活中
What kind of situation will it break into?
都會破入到什麼樣的情況
it can change its behavior instantly
它可以立刻就改變它的行為
then reduce its risk
然後降低它的風險
So this is our cooperation with the Information Office
所以這是我們跟資訊所的合作
Now there is a small
現在有的這樣子一個小型的
A portable version of the tiny sensor
隨身版的微型感測器
This tiny sensor could also be added to the street
這個微型感測器也可以加在街邊
with solar panels
有太陽能板
can then be transferred instantly to our database
然後可以即時傳輸到我們的資料庫
Even we have an indoor sensor like this
甚至我們也有這樣子一個室內的感測器
OK
OK
The sensors in this room are also
這室內的感測器也是
The data can be viewed online in real time
資料可以即時上網至即時來看
At present, we have placed more than a dozen families
目前的話我們已經放在十幾個家庭
This is in a certain house
這個在某一個家戶裡面的
After months of data collection
我們收集了幾個月的資料之後
Also found A strange
也發現A奇怪
Why does he have a fixed number of peaks every day
他怎麼每天都會有固定的幾個peak
Spike concentrations of two or three
兩個或三個的尖峰濃度
Later I found out that he has the habit of offering incense in the morning and evening
後來才知道說他有早晚進香的習慣
And he cooks at home too
而且他也會在家烹調
So we reminded him right away
所以我們就立刻提醒他了
He's very glad we reminded him
他非常高興我們提醒他
This aunt also asked us later
這個阿姨他後來也還問我們說
How can I reduce his concentration during this goodbye?
要怎麼樣可以降低他這個拜拜的時候的濃度
We just reminded him to open the doors and windows
我們就提醒他就是要打開門窗
So his concentration dropped a lot later
所以後來他的濃度就降低很多
So this is what I think these tiny sensors
所以這就是我覺得這些微型感測器
possible future development
未來的可以的發展
is to remind everyone to change their behavior
就是即使提醒大家改變行為
reduce your health risks
然後降低自己的健康風險
If we still hope in the future
那未來我們還會希望的話
It is for this urban traffic flow
是針對這個都市車流
This is a collaboration with Mr. Fengyuan and the others
這是跟資訊所料逢源老師他們合作
They have very good image recognition technology
他們有很好的影像辨識的技術
traffic in the community
在社區裡面的車流
I think it must be an important factor causing the increase in pollution in this community
我覺得一定是造成這個社區污染增量很重要的因子
Because there is no such good technology
因為沒有這麼好的技術
used to use very expensive cameras
以前都要用很貴的照相機
to analyze
才能去解析出來
Now their technology can be used in general
現在他們的技術可以是用一般
Everyone sees the police station hanging on the street
大家看到掛在街邊的警察局
or a government camera
或者是政府的影像器
You can analyze the direction of the car
就可以解析出這個車子的走向
And it can identify the car type
而且它可以辨識出車種
Of course, this actually has many challenges.
當然這個其實有很多的挑戰
including say it you see there are so many different intersections
包括說它你看有這麼多不同的路口
it has a different turn
它有不同的轉向
How to use a computer to directly identify
怎麼用電腦的方式去直接辨識
Big cars and small cars can also be identified very well
大車小車還可以辨識得很不錯
it has some shadowing due to the low angle
它有一些因為低角度的遮蔽
So it's a bad situation
所以比較不好的情況
But otherwise
但是其他來講
I think generally speaking, it is to analyze the traffic flow.
我覺得大致上來看是分析這個車流量
is well analyzed
是分析的排滿好的
In the future, we will cooperate with our observers on the street
將來我們就要跟我們街邊的觀測儀起來配合
So we are not afraid that this service company is lying to us
所以我們就不怕這個服司公司在騙我們
We'll then be able to actually
我們以後就可以實際上在
Know the increase in emissions of vehicles that are not driving and the factors of emissions
知道說在不上行駛的車子的排放的增量跟排放的因子
OK
OK
So if we do these emission factors and so on
所以我們做這些排放因子等等的話
I hope it can be accumulated in our exposure mode in the future
希望將來都可以累積到我們的暴露模式裡面去
OK
OK
Well, here's the stuff we've done over the years
好 這是我們過去這些年來做的資料
Atmospheric
在世外大氣
this
這個
On weekends, I'd better go to the suburbs for a walk
週末的話還是多去郊區走走
Because it is true that the concentration in the suburbs is relatively low
因為它的確實郊外的濃度是比較低
That secondhand smoke is the scariest
那二手煙是最可怕的
OK so try not to smoke this one
OK 所以這個盡量不要吸煙
And after smoking your
而且吸了煙之後你的
The cilia in this lung will stop
這個肺部的纖毛會停止
30 minutes of inactivity
30分鐘不活動
In other words, all your
也就是說在這過程中你所有的
All the dirt on the outside tends to get implanted deep in your lungs
所有外面的髒東西都會常去植入到你的肺的深部
OK
OK
so this can
所以這個可以
Tell your smoking friends
轉告一下吸煙的朋友們
ask them to smoke as little as possible
請他們就盡量少吸煙
Okay, the last mention is to say
好 最後提到一下就是說
In fact, it's not just the researchers who are very concerned about this PLO question.
其實不只是研究者對於這個PLO點問很在意
In fact, some civic groups
其實一些公民團體
They also spontaneously put this
他們也很自發性的把這個
I cooperate with information agency
我跟資訊所合作
The prototype of a sensor developed by Mr. Lin Zhi and the others
林志老師他們所主要研發的一個感測器的原型
after they improved
他們改善了之後
There are also some private companies willing to mass produce
也有一些民間的公司願意量產
Cooperate with some municipal governments, etc.
跟一些市政府合作等等
This is one of the airborne sensor network
這個就是一個空母感測網的一個
A Cooperative Mechanism of Industry, Government and Academia
產官學的一個合作的機制
I also invited experts from European and American countries two weeks ago
我前兩個禮拜也請了歐美的國家的專家
they were also surprised
他們也很訝異
It is our air carrier sensor network in Taiwan
就是我們台灣的空母感測網
This has accumulated to more than 2,000 sensors in the province
這樣已經累積到2000多個感測器在全省
Although he still has some accuracy problems
雖然說他還有一些正確性上的問題
But this can be improved by scientific correction
但這個可以用科學的校正來加以這個改善
Finally, I would like to thank the hospital for this sustainable
最後我要謝謝這個院方對於這個永續
Most of what I just reported was
我剛剛報告的大部分都是
A collaborative effort of this sustainable project
這個永續計劃的一個合作的成果
This is a cross-disciplinary team
這個是要跨領域的團隊
Thanks to my partners
謝謝我的這些合作夥伴們
We also want to say something about the results of our sustainable projects
我們也希望說我們這些永續計劃的成果的話
There can be some parts that can be used as a reference for government units
能夠有一些部分 能夠給政府單位參考
and can be translated into policy
而且能夠轉化成政策
able to actually help everyone
能夠實際說幫助大家
Can reduce health risks
能夠降低健康的風險
protect our health
保障我們的健康
thank you all
謝謝大家
Thanks
謝謝
Thank you, Mr. Long, very brilliant
謝謝龍老師非常精采的
This introduction to 2D Hygan PM2.5
這個對二維亥根PM2.5的介紹
now we have time left
現在我們還剩下的時間
we're going to be open to questions
我們就要開放提問
If you ask questions today
今天如果各位問問題的話
We have a copy of the current issue of Scientific Man here
我們這邊有一份這當期的科學人雜誌
because there is an article in it
因為裡面有一篇文章
Then give it to the friend who asked the question
那送給提問的朋友
we have seven on site
我們有七本在現場
So the first seven people can get this magazine
所以前面七個人可以得到這一份雜誌
If there are other problems later
如果說後面還有其他的問題
we don't have it right now
我們現在手邊沒有
just wait
就請你等下
Please register with the staff when you go out
請問一下出去的時候跟工作人員登記一下
We just have questions today
我們今天只要有提問
We'll deliver the magazine to you again
我們就會再把雜誌送到您的手上
ok , thanks then , one of you to start
好,那謝謝,請來一位開始
Excuse me
請問一下
where is it
在哪裡?我們舉一下,這邊好
because I looked
因為我看了一下
That thermal power plant in Taiwan
那台灣的那個火力化電廠
That PM2.5
那個PM2.5
Can you tell us about his numerical value?
他的數值可不可以跟我們介紹一下
Do you mean the data he released?
您是說他排放出來的數據嗎?
This will probably go to the EPA
這個很可能要去環保署
What he said about the chimneys of thermal power plants
他針對火力發電廠的煙囪的話
They all have a direct
他們都有一個直接的
one...
一個...
You say it is an observation instrument
你再說是觀測的儀器
What he is observing is actually a light transmittance
他在觀測的其實是一個透光率
OK, this is connected to the environmental protection bureaus in various places
OK,這個是連到各地方的環保局
And now they are also connected to the Environmental Protection Agency
然後目前也都是有連到環保署
have this business information
都有這份商業資料
yes
是
I don't have one for thermal power plants
我沒有針對火力發電廠的
thermal power plant for me
火力發電廠對我來講
It is an environment that affects the surrounding environment
它是一個影響周介環境的
an important factor
一個重要的因子
OK
OK
Then it has been mixed with the corona
那它已經被菌暈混合了
so for me
所以對我來講
It is a monitoring station belonging to the Environmental Protection Agency
它是屬於環保署的監測站
will study
會研究的
That is to say, the concentration that will be analyzed
就是說會分析出來的這個濃度
Then I am researching mainly
那我在研究最主要是
Above this ambient concentration
在這個周介環境濃度以上
We'll also have some community polluters
我們還會有一些社區污染源所
incremental increment
增加的增量
even our personal behavior
甚至是我們的個人的行為
will add this part of it again
還會再把它增量的這個部分
This is the focus of my research
這個是我研究的重點
Thanks
謝謝
ok this one
好,這位
Hello Mr. Rong
Rong老師你好
excuse me, may I ask
我問一下
Just two main questions
剛剛主要兩個問題
inside a graph of your show
一個您秀的圖表裡面
there is a 30
有一個30
We say that it will be dangerous after 32 o'clock
我們說32點多就開始有危害
But your paper got 36.8
但是你那個紙取到36.8
I don't know why he took that paper
我不知道為什麼他取那個紙
The number of days is less or what is the meaning of this
天數少還是這個意義是什麼
This is the first question
這是第一個問題
Second question you have a line plot of the WGBT distribution
第二個問題你有一個WGBT分布的一個線圖
It looks like it works well together
看起來它的協力很好
that approach a straight line at a time
那趨近一次一個直線
It stands to reason that such data should be more suitable for prediction.
照理說這樣的數據應該是比較適合預測的
Didn't our colleagues from the Meteorological Bureau say
那我們氣象局的同事不是說
The introduction said that if this is the case, our forecast is very accurate.
介紹說如果這樣的話我們預測很準
Then can we push back and say
那我們是不是可以去推回去說
Such a linear function comes out to predict the value of
這樣的一個線性函數出來預測的值
is it true what we say
是不是真的像我們說的
it is more predictive
它是比較有預測性的
Probably these two questions
大概這兩個問題
Ok so the first one is 36.8 for this WGBT
好 所以第一個是這個WGBT的36.8
in fact it is
事實上是這樣
Because if we want to issue hazard warnings,
因為我們如果要發布危害預警的話
If you post every day for the whole summer
你如果是一整個夏天每天都發布
That's the same thing as not publishing
那就等於沒發布是一樣的事情
There is no way to achieve the effect of early warning
就是沒有辦法達到預警的效果
Because in fact, the meteorological unit is forecasting this situation every time.
因為其實現在氣象單位每次在預報這個情況
I will remind everyone every day
每天起手已經會提醒大家
It's just that there may be a heat hazard, etc.
就是有可能有熱危害等等
That grows police words every day
那每天都在發育警的話
it doesn't work
就沒有這個作用
So to find the nine percent
那所以要找出那個百分之九數
36.84% 99% quantile
36.84% 99%分位數
That is to say, it is the one percent at the front end.
就是等於說是最前端的那個百分之一
right
對
So if we target
那所以如果是我們針對
the top one percent
那個最前端的百分之一
special reminder
特別去提醒的話
For example, let everyone
譬如說真的就讓大家
They all reduce going out
都是比較減少出門
It is even said that there may be some more
甚至說可能會有一些更
including things like yelling with electricity
包括像是些用電大呼
Maybe don't use electricity at that time
那時候可能先不要用電
Because it is likely that everyone wants to turn on the air conditioner
因為很可能大家都是要開冷氣
or how
或怎麼樣
words like this
類似像這樣子的話
may be more effective
可能會更有效果
so this is
所以這個是
I think it is the consideration of the administrative unit
我想是行政單位的考量
they won't either
他們也不會
So this value is not fixed
所以這個值不是固定
if later
如果以後
About the market effect is higher
關於市效應更高
or what he still raises like this
或什麼他還會這樣上調
yes
是
Actually that's why
其實這也是為什麼
set the warning of this heat hazard
定這個熱危害的預警的
The limit is only
預限只是
is so difficult
是這麼困難
because it's actually changing all the time
因為它其實一直在變動
A study in the United States also pointed out that
那美國的一個研究也指出
30 years ago and 30 years later
30年前跟30年後
the current one
現在的那個
They do heat hazards for this
他們做熱危害的這個
The body does have, it should be said, an adjustment function
身體確實是有 應該是說一個調適作用
That is, our body will slowly adjust to
就是我們身體會慢慢地去調整成
We can cope with hotter conditions
我們可以因應比較熱的情況
Now I'm more worried
那現在比較擔心就是說
In the context of the whole of our response to climate change shocks
在這個整個我們因應氣候變遷衝擊的情況之下
Some people can adjust to the past, some people can't
有些人可以調適的過去 有些人沒有辦法
So we still need the government to find a way
所以我們還是要政府 還是要想辦法
Remind everyone with an early warning
用預警的方式來提醒大家
How come under some relatively hot conditions
怎麼在一些比較熱的情況之下
Able to do a good job in self-health management and self-protection
能夠做好自我的健康的管理 自我防護
So this is a purpose of heat warning
所以這個是熱預警的一個目的
This is the first point
這是第一點
the second you say that
那第二個您說那個
we predicted this
我們預測的這個
this this line
這個這條線
It is because meteorological units use complex physical and chemical
是因為氣象單位都是用很複雜的物理化學的
This model is used to make predictions
這個模式來做預測
OK so all we can do now is
OK 那所以我們現在能夠做的就是
The complex physicochemical patterns they predicted
他們所預測出來的很複雜的物理化學模式
made predictions
做出來的預測值
We directly selected the temperature, humidity, wind speed and solar radiation
我們直接選取了溫度濕度風速跟太陽輻射
convert it into WBGT
把它轉化 轉化成WBGT
Then compare it with our actual measured value
然後跟我們實際的測值去做比對
OK, our line came out like this
OK 我們那條線是這樣出來的
So you mean to use that line to make predictions directly
所以 您是說用那條線直接去做預測的話
Probably not what weather units are used to
可能不是氣象單位他們習慣的用法
their words still apply
他們的話還是會用
Because they also have to take into account the flow of air masses and so on.
因為他們還要考慮到氣團流動等等的這個
i mean
我的意思是說
can i just ask
可不可以請問一下就是
Maybe discuss it with the teacher of the Data Institute next time
下次可能跟數據所的老師先討論一下
Because for us if the linear content
因為對我們來講如果是線性含數
then you might be a math room
那你可能是一個數學室
then you can assess what the possible weaknesses are
那你可以評估出來說可能的弱點是什麼
Or we should say that the surrounding area of ​​your linear derivative has the highest occurrence rate
或是我們應該說你這個線性含數周邊都是發生率最大的
yes but that's not our purpose
是 可是這不是我們的目的
We do that for the purpose of
我們做那個目的其實是在
Check whether our measured values ​​are accurate to the predicted values
檢驗一下我們的實測值跟預測值準不準
That is to say, are they predicting well?
也就是說他們預測的好不好
Because the weather bureau is very concerned about what they're predicting
因為氣象局非常擔心他們預測的
their models predict bad things
他們的模式預測出來的東西不好
So they are afraid to issue this warning
所以他們都不敢去發布這個預警
no meaning
No 意思
So their purpose is to say
所以他們的目的是說
Check that their models are currently predictive
檢驗一下他們的模式目前是可以用作預測
That's what we actually measure
那跟我們實際上測量
These two places are also very close
這兩處也很接近
In this way, they are more at ease
這樣的話他們比較放心
Can do early warning of thermal hazards
可以去做熱危害的預警
So our purpose is actually like this
所以我們的目的其實是這樣子
do you mean
是不是意思是說
The prediction method of using the math room to push is inaccurate
用數學室去推的預測方式是不準的
No, it means meteorological units
不是 而是說氣象單位
they want to test
他們要考
Meteorological unit to predict tomorrow's weather
氣象單位去預測明天天氣
It is actually a very complex pattern in the run
它其實是一個很複雜的模式在run的
It is not a simple math room to push directly
它不是用一個簡單的數學室直接去推的
yes
是
It's just that the food is more difficult
就是食物上面是比較困難的
ok we study too
好 我們也學習
We can discuss more later
完了以後再可以多加討論
Okay, thank you
好 謝謝
there is one over there
那邊有一位
yes
是
you say zhang hao
您說張浩
i just mentioned
我剛才有提到
cataract problem
白內障的問題
you say you mean
你說您就是說
Under climate change maybe because of UV light and so on
氣候變遷之下可能是因為紫外線等等
Effects on Cataracts
對於白內障的影響
this aspect
這一方面
So far I haven't researched that
是目前我還沒有研究到那麼
so deep
那麼高深的這個地步
The data analysis we are doing now
我們現在目前做的資料分析的話
The comparison is focused on the
比較是著重在對於
Neovascular disease Lung disease
新血管疾病 肺臟疾病
Kidney disease, etc.
腎臟功能疾病等
some effects of this
這方面的一些影響
Then there are some studies pointing to skin disease
那還有一些研究指出是皮膚病
that for this
那對於這個
This part of white goods is dirty
白電臟這個部分
We haven't done any research on this yet
我們還沒有去做這方面的研究
Thanks
謝謝
In the future we can move towards this
以後我們可以可以朝這方面
ok sir wait a minute
好 這位先生等一下
May I ask if the current technology can lower the temperature?
請問一下現在的科技可不可以讓溫度降下來
What can make the temperature of the earth
有哪些可以讓地球的溫度
or technology that cools the room down
或是讓室內溫度降下來的技術
Room temperature
室內溫度
Indoor temperature is cold air
室內溫度就是冷氣
But I said the temperature of the entire earth
可是我說整個地球溫度
I am not in favor of using this geoengineering method to cool down
我是不太贊成用這個地球工程的方式去降溫
Because I think there must be another sequelae
因為我覺得一定會有另外的後遺症
This sequela is likely to be borne by people all over the world
這個後遺症很可能是全世界人要共同承擔
So I don't quite agree with scientists going to risk this blood
所以我不太贊成科學家要去冒這個血
Come do the job of cooling the planet
來做這個地球降溫的工作
Or use this volley to clear it
還是用這個伏地抽清
It should be renewable energy
就是應該是用再生能源
before reducing carbon emissions
然後之前要減少碳排放
can slowly reduce the pace of climate change
能夠慢慢降低這個氣候變遷的腳步
I think it's more of a way to draw the ground.
我覺得這是比較是伏地抽清的方式
Thanks
謝謝
you talk about heat hazards
您講到熱危害
Mainly it's like turning on the air conditioner
主要就是好像開冷氣
Can I have indoor plants?
請問室內植物可不可以
helps reduce temperature
有助於降低溫度
Another reason I ask this is
我會這樣問的還有另外一個原因就是
I didn't see Mr. Lin Zhiming from the original branch in time
我不及時看到原分所的林志明老師
he is tidying the garden
他在整理庭園
Clean up the garden in the middle of the former branch office
整理那個原分所中間的那個庭園
He said it was hard to find
他說原定不好找
So I would say plants have something to do with this
所以我想說植物跟這個都關係
well this is a
好 這是一個
It's that plant that does provide shade
是那個植物確實有遮陽的作用
So it's not just
所以那個其實不只是
In fact, the urban green space
就是其實都市綠地
will have a cooling effect on local areas
都會對於局部地區都會有降溫的作用
In the house, planting plants in the corridor and so on will indeed have a cooling effect
家裡面的話 走廊上等等 種植物確實是會有降溫的作用
Some scientific literature has some such reports
有些科學文獻有些這樣的報導
In fact, the researchers of our doctoral association have also done some urban green space planning on the impact of cooling
其實我們博士會研究員也做了一些都市綠地的規劃對於降溫的影響
So we also have measured rulings in this area, etc.
所以我們也有這方面的實測的執政之類
And it can provide some job opportunities, which is a problem
而且可以提供一些工作機會 這是一個問題
Then, at the beginning, you said that 90% of the TV room and theater room are green.
然後請問 您開始的時候說電房 劇房的綠造九成
And internet surveys are cheap but young people
然後網路調查雖然很便宜 但是都是年輕人
Is there a way to combine
那有沒有可能一種結合的方式
That means doing some research online and asking him to ask his family.
就是說用網路調查 然後請他去問他的家人
Then use those cost gaps as lectures or commentary to encourage them
然後把那些成本的差距用來講監或者是講評來鼓勵他們
Thank you. We've actually thought about this before.
謝謝您 我們其實以前有想過這件事
But the more troublesome thing is that you have to train the middleman
可是比較麻煩的是說 你要訓練那個中間人
In fact, all of us interviewers have to come to us for three days of training.
其實我們這些訪員都要來我們這邊經過三整天的訓練
Actually quite hard
其實還蠻辛苦的
So if we use questionnaires to survey young people on the Internet
所以我們如果是用問券調查網路上的年輕人
We're still trying to figure out how to train this young man
我們還想辦法去訓練這個年輕人
and then ask his grandparents
然後再去問他的祖父母
we thought about it
我們當初是有這樣想過
But in practice, it is quite difficult
可是實務操作上其實還蠻困難的
Thanks
謝謝
Another question is
還有一個問題是
We talk about the situation at home and abroad, just the opposite
我們講說國內國外的情況正好相反
It’s just that in foreign countries, their interiors are rather dirty
就是在國外是他們室內反而比較髒
The opposite is true in Taiwan
在台灣的情形正好相反
You are talking about the comparison between indoor and outdoor
您講的是說室內跟室外比較
Is it possible for the two countries to be at the same time?
那有沒有可不可以兩國的同時
definitely worth comparing
絕對值得比較
Of course we are worse than America
我們當然是比美國要糟糕
much worse
糟糕不少
how bad is it
糟糕的程度怎麼樣
We can use the data on the Internet to see
我們就可以用網路上的數據去看
Because many places in the United States
因為美國很多地方
It is possible to meet this annual average
它是可以符合這個年平均
15 micrograms per cubic meter
15微克美利方公尺的
Some can even be better than 10
甚至是可以有的會好到10以下
Then Taiwan basically only has Huadong
那台灣基本上就只有花東
Only barely around 15
才勉強大概是15左右
That is to say, although they are dirty indoors
也就是說他們雖然室內髒
But still cleaner than our outdoor
但還是比我們的室外乾淨
this one
這個一顆
good
好
Our one will be right back
我們那一位馬上回來
can i hear you answer this question
是不是可以聽你回答這個問題
Whether we are in Europe or Asia
我們不管在歐洲還是亞洲
Pollution both outdoors and indoors
室外跟室內都產生污染
but in asia
但是在亞洲
the outdoor pollution
這些室外的污染
Once inside, it settles
進到室內之後它就沉澱下來
so every day we have to wipe the table
所以每天我們要擦桌子
is a sedimented
是一個沉澱下來的
but in europe
但在歐洲
Because outdoor pollution is less
因為室外的污染的產生比較少
So indoor cooking is relatively high
所以室內煮東西的東西比較高
this is relatively
這是相對而言
We're down because we're indoors
我們是因為在室內都降下來了
so viewers come
所以觀眾們來
the air will be clean
空氣就會乾淨
Thank you Dean Li
謝謝李院長
Thank you for the supplementary answer
謝謝補充答案
Just this gentleman
剛剛這位先生
I just noticed that a data is the data ratio
我剛有注意到一個數據就是經過相濡的數據比
much smaller than that of a smoker
遠比經過抽菸者的還要小很多
This is not what I expected
這跟預期的不太一樣
That is to say, it should be one
就是說應該相濡應該是一個
It should be that the so-called BN2.5 data will sing very high
就是應該會所謂的BN2.5的數據會唱很高
The result of that tiny detector
那個微型偵測器的結果
That's because you really smoke
那是因為真的抽菸的
After a smoker's stats are so high
經過一個抽菸者的數據就這麼高了
Or is it a detector issue?
還是說偵測器的問題
we passed by
我們經過的
Are you talking about the information about the night market?
你是說夜市的那個資料嗎
yes
是
The night market information is actually three smokers
夜市資料其實是三個抽菸者
And they've been smoking there for a while
而且他們在那邊抽了好一陣子了
So this time answer first
所以這次回答第一
that kissing words
那個相濡的話
we just pass by
我們就只是經過一下子
We're not actually that close to it
我們其實並沒有那麼靠近它
didn't mean to
也不是故意要
But speaking of distance
但是說實在就距離來講的話
We may be close to that distance
我們可能跟那個相濡的距離
Probably about the same as the smoker
跟那個吸菸者可能還差不多
So in fact, it is to look at the inside of the temple.
所以其實就是看它廟這個相濡裡面
A little more is actually related to how many boxes
稍多好跟多少支箱其實是有關係的
So that's the result of our test
所以那是我們那次的檢測的結果
ok, this one has
好,這位有
let me ask
我請問一下
on your side
你這一邊的時候
That's this number for PM2.5
那是PM2.5的這個數字
It is obvious that the graph line has dropped in recent years
那明顯的時候這幾年那個圖線下降
But in our impression
但是在我們的那個的印象中
Because our PM2.5
因為我們那個PM2.5
So the Air and Oxygen Bureau exploded in the past few years
所以那個氣氧局是這幾年才就爆出來
just started to have these forecasts
才開始有這些的預報
that and we see what a place it is these years
那並且我們看到是這幾年什麼一個地方
It seems that they are all red red red red red red red red red red red red red red red red red red red red red red red red
好像都是紅紅紅紅紅紅紅紅紅紅紅紅的
a lot of them
都一大堆了
So in our sense
所以在我們的那個感覺上
It seems that PM2.5 is very serious now
好像PM2.5的時候現在是很嚴重
There is also a second question
還有第二個問題是
I used to ask that Puri
我曾經到問那個普里
when purina side
普里那一邊的時候
We used to say that Puri is like good water
我們以前都是說普里好像好水的時候
is a good view
是好風景
best air
空氣最好的
But when Purina turned out to be
但是普里那竟然的時候是
When the whole province of Taiwan
台灣全省的時候
2.5% seems to be the highest today
今天2.5%好像是最高的
why is that
這是為什麼
ok , to answer your first question
好,是回答您第一個問題
The first question is actually usually
第一個問題其實通常是
Pollution is more serious in winter
冬天的污染比較嚴重
especially in south central
尤其是中南部的時候
Pollution is serious in winter
冬天污染比較嚴重
But if we average it out
但是我們如果把它平均下來的話
It is actually an annual average
它其實是一個年平均
In summer, it is actually less polluted
就是夏天的時候它其實是污染低的
OK
OK
So if you look at the annual average in winter and summer
所以冬天跟夏天你看年平均的話
will be averaged out
就會被平均掉的
Then you said that it is red every day
那您說那個每天都紅通通
That's actually mostly in winter.
那其實多半都是在冬天的時候
especially in this
尤其是在這個
There is indeed a lot of pollution in Kaohsiung.
高雄那邊確實是非常多的這個污染
Actually quite serious
其實滿嚴重的
right
對
Then there is another question, that is
那還有另外一個問題就是說
Back then when the environmental groups released this air pollution period
當初環保團體在放這個空污期的時候
It's often an hour's worth of data
它常常是用一個小時的數據
To compare the environmental protection number is actually an average of 24 hours
去比對環保數其實是24小時的平均的一個
that is
就是說
This is the standard of air pollution
就是空污的這個標準
OK, it's actually not suitable
OK,其實是不適合的
Theoretically, it is necessary to accumulate 24 hours
理論上是要累積24小時
Ability to go beyond the 24 hour standard
才能去比24小時的標準
There is no one-hour standard for the environmental protection number
環保數目前還沒有一個小時的標準
then we actually think
那我們其實認為
Might want to consider having an hour standard
可能要考慮要有一個小時的標準
Because like I just mentioned
因為像我剛剛提到
In fact, P2.5 is for acute
其實P2.5對急性的話
It actually has acute health effects
它其實有急性的健康效應
Then why is there no acute
那目前為什麼還沒有急性的
It is the standard of one hour of agricultural degree
就是一個小時的農度的標準
because there is no good scientific data to back it up
是因為還沒有很好的科學數據的佐證
Tell us what kind of farming it is
告訴我們說是到什麼樣農度的話
There will be such acute health damage
會有這樣的急性的健康的傷害產生
So if there is good scientific evidence
所以如果有比較好的科學佐證
Then the future can slowly move towards
那未來慢慢就可以朝向
How to build such an hour of air though
怎麼樣去建立這樣的一個小時的空氣固然
Restricted standards to move forward
限制的標準來前進
The second question is Puri
第二個問題是普里
Puri's problem is
普里的問題是
Puri actually
普里其實
let me say it again
我再說一下
when puri was the one
普里的時候是那個
We used to say Puri was the cleanest
我們以前都說普里是最乾淨的
But in the past few years
但是這幾年來的時候
when puri's side of them
普里的他們那一邊的時候
The information found is the most serious P2.5 in Taiwan
所找到的資料是全台灣可能P2.5最嚴重的
why is that so
那為什麼會這樣
It's Puri this we actually
是普里這個我們其實
The whole team around the center
環遍中心的整個團隊
Including myself, I have been the deputy director of customs clearance in the lead
包括我自己在內就有做通關副主任領先
And then we're actually here
然後我們其實是在這
Since last year there has been pollution targeting this area in central Puri
從去年開始有針對普里跟中部的這地區的污染
have started doing some research
有開始進行一些研究
This part of Napuri may be derived from the part of Taichung
那普里的這個部分有可能是從台中部分
from Taichung
從台中傳進去的
There are also some possibly local motorbikes
那也有一些有可能是當地的汽機車
Because the accumulation is there and can't get out
因為累積在那邊出不去
Because after all, it is a situation in a relatively mountainous area.
因為它畢竟是一個比較山裡面的一個情況
Both are possible
這兩個都有可能
For now, we'll need more scientific evidence
那目前的話我們還會需要更多的科學證據
to know why
才能夠知道說到底是為什麼
It will cause such a serious pollution in Puri
會造成普里這麼高的嚴重的這個污染
Thanks
謝謝
good
好
There is a kid here
這邊有一位小朋友
Hello teacher
老師好
i want to ask
我想請問一下
Which method does the teacher recommend to prevent weak hazards?
老師比較推薦哪一種防範弱危害的方法
What kind
哪一種
do you defend yourself
你自自我防範嗎
just at home
就是平常在家中
I usually wash my face at home
平常在家中就是常常洗臉
Heat dissipation and drinking the Aiyu just mentioned
散熱跟喝剛剛講的愛玉
I think it's more cooling
我覺得是比較能夠降溫
and not to the body
而且不會對身體
Because Aiyu it's not so cool
因為愛玉它並不是那麼的涼
so you know girls sometimes
所以你知道女孩子有時候
Don't drink anything too cold
不能喝太涼的東西
But Aiyu should be fine
但是愛玉應該還好
So for the body there will be no
所以對於身體不會有
Too bad some of the other side effects
太糟糕的一些其他的副作用
second question
第二問題
ask about the room
請問一下房間
Now there are a lot of air purifiers
現在有很多的是空氣清淨劑
Can it filter PH2.5 and PH1.0
那它可否過濾PH2.5跟PH1.0
What about indoor air quality
那對於室內的空氣品質
Is there an actual effect
是否有實際的效應
there are some indeed in this
有一些確實在這個
I know some researchers
我知道有些研究者
some of the air cleaners they sell for homes
他們針對室售的一些空氣清淨劑
But that was done seven or eight years ago
不過那是七八年前做的
Basically only one effective
基本上只有一款有效
Now the technology is better
那現在的話技術比較好
So there should be more effective
所以的話應該會有更多的比較有效
Then I'm going to talk about the only one they made that worked seven or eight years ago
那我要講說七八年前他們做的唯一有效那個
In fact, it's too expensive, and most people won't use it at all.
其實是太貴了一般人根本不會用的
so you know it's
所以你就知道就是
i mean
我的意思就是
Generally affordable ones are likely to have no effect
一般買得起的很可能都沒有什麼效果
i'm embarrassed to say that
我不好意思要這樣講
but
但是
But now technology has improved
可是現在技術有進步
From another perspective
那從另外一方面來講
This question to students we should say
這個對學生的問題我們應該說
Actually, I haven't tested it.
其實沒有檢驗過我就是
I don't know. I didn't test it myself.
不知道那我自己是沒有檢驗
Ok, then I also buy air purifiers at home
ok那我自己家裡也有買空氣清淨劑
Then I should try it next time with mine
那我下次應該試一下就是用我的這個
simple setting
簡單設定
Micro-sense test to see if it works
微型感測試一下到底有沒有效
Thank you teacher for your answer
謝謝老師的答覆
Thanks
謝謝
There are many kinds of air proximity devices
那個空氣接近器有很多種很多種
It's only used in hospitals now
現在只有在醫院用的
this in the hospital
醫院的這個
Air Proximator
用的空氣接近器
about one step
大概一步要
three hundred thousand dollars
三十萬塊錢
that for pm2
那個對pm2
Today I was helpful, others were not
今天我有幫助 其他的沒有幫助
Thank you, Dean Li, for helping me answer this question.
謝謝李院長幫我回答這個問題
This is the authority on chemistry
這是化學的權威
Okay, we have about four minutes.
好 我們大概還有四分鐘
let me ask the last question myself
我自己問最後一個問題好了
Because you can see the distribution of your WBGT in your
因為在你的 看到你的那個WBGT的那個分布
You said that the highest and worst place in New Taipei City is Yonghe
你說新北市最高最差的地方是永和那邊
Because it may be very crowded and crowded there.
因為那邊可能是非常人口也很聚集
Then there are many houses and the streets are relatively narrow
然後房子也很多 街道也比較窄
The worst place in Taipei City is Zhongzheng District
台北市最差的地方是中正區
It's a bit Zhongzheng District, my impression is
這有點 中正區我的印象是
This population is not that much
這個人口沒有那麼多
Then the streets are wider
然後他街道也比較寬
Yes you know why that place
是 你們知道為什麼會那個地方
It's still a lot of water, there's too much Pojoro, or something
還是水一大堆 波幽露太多了還是什麼
Why is it worse over there?
為什麼會那邊比較差
If we do this, of course we counted this at that time
我們這個的話 我們當然那個時候有算這個
Just mentioned that heat island
剛剛提到那個熱島
heat island effect
熱島效應
The heat island effect is actually not in Zhongzheng District
熱島效應其實中正區其實不是
not the worst part
不是最糟糕的部分
So we are also curious
所以我們自己也很好奇
But you can see that the area
但是你可以看到說那一塊地區
So it is also related to the temperature distribution at that time
那所以也是跟當時的溫度分布
is about
是有關
That's actually like Nangang's words
那其實像南港的話
Relatively speaking, the temperature in Nangang
相對來講南港的溫度
In fact, it is not as high as downtown Taipei.
其實就沒有台北市中心高
So this is also related to the temperature at that time
所以這也是跟當時的溫度有關
right
對
good
好
Then our time is almost up
那我們時間也差不多了
we are very thankful today
我們今天非常謝謝
Teacher Long Shijun gave us such a wonderful speech
龍士俊老師給我們這麼精采的演講
We give him another round of applause
我們給他再一次熱烈的掌聲
Thanks
謝謝
thank you all
謝謝大家